<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A narrative written by E. Settle.</title>
            <author>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59326</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10691</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11907453</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11907453</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50755</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59326)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50755)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 511:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A narrative written by E. Settle.</title>
                  <author>Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 25 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by Thomas Graves for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>On the Popish Plot and the evidence of Titus Oates.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50755:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50755:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NARRATIVE.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN BY <hi>E. Settle.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Humano capiti cervicem pictor equinam</l>
               <l>Jungere ſi velit, &amp; varias inducere plumas</l>
               <l>Undique collatis membris, ut turpiter atrum</l>
               <l>Deſinat in piſcem, Mulier formoſa ſuperne,</l>
               <l>Spectatum admiſſi riſum teneatis, amici.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Thomas Graves</hi> for the Author. 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50755:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50755:2"/>
            <head>To his Honour'd Friend Sir <hi>Thomas Taylor</hi> Baronett.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OUR promiſed Acceptance has lent me Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to make you this Preſent, yet what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Pretenſions your own Goodneſs has giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en me for this Preſumption, or the Preſent it ſelf might otherwiſe obtain, the unhallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hand that offers it, is enough to make it undeſerve the Glory it claims. However I lay hold of your generous Condeſcenſion, and fixe your Name before this Peice, not onely as a Patron; but a Precedent to all Loyal Gentlemen to forgive my paſt faults as you have done.</p>
            <p>'Tis with this Deſign I ſhelter my ſelfe under the Protection of a Perſon of ſuch Eminent Worth, and ſo high in the Liſt of Honour: For no man has a Soul more intirely devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and a Loyalty more firme to his Prince; and to heighten the Bleſſing, no man a Courage more daring to ſignalize that Loyalty, when ever his Prince ſhall call for't. But, Sir, as your Country may be proud of you in either Capacity, may it never want you in the laſt. May our <hi>Caeſar</hi> Reign like a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Auguſtus;</hi> have his <hi>Janus</hi> Temple ever ſhut, and his Peace for ever Floriſhing. And that he may not onely have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Prayers, and hearty Endeavours of all good Subjects to give him it: I hope he has ſome Prognoſticks even from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf to aſſure it him. For certainly that Noon-day Star that ſhined at his Nativity, and that Miracle that ſhined more bright, his Bloodleſs Reſtoration, both from the Immediate Finger of God, are undoubted Forerunners of ſome more then common Glories attending him; Thoſe Divine Propheticks that he neither can be what the Malice of his Enemies would Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter him, nor ſhall be what their Trechery would make him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:50755:3"/>But, Sir, before I aſpire to the Favour of ſo Honourable a Friend as your ſelf, I ought firſt to ſhake off that Load that holds me down even below your meaneſt Thoughts. And truly Sir, as I want no little refining to purge my Droſs away, ſo I am reſolved to be ſo candid in my Confeſſion, that in Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a perfect Abjuration of my paſt Ills, Ile give both Your ſelf and the World as plain a Picture of my faults and follies as my ſevereſt Enemies can or would paint them for me.</p>
            <p>About ten years ſince I writ a Play call'd, <hi>The Empreſs of Morocco,</hi> and ſome time after I carryed it to His <hi>Majeſties Theatre,</hi> where in the height of Mr. <hi>Harts</hi> Health and Excellence, I flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd my ſelf with aſſurance of wonderful ſucceſs from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of then ſo able a Company: but upon former Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with His Highneſſes Servants, they made a complaint to their <hi>Royal Maſter,</hi> &amp; got the Play commanded back again to their own Play-Houſe, where tho' His <hi>Royal Highneſs,</hi> upon conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to hear his Servants in ſo humble a Cauſe, upon the Circumſtances againſt me, did nothing but the higheſt Peice of Juſtice, yet Self-juſtification and my defeated Vanity begat that malignant reſentment, that <hi>manet alta mente repoſtum,</hi> and engende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that unhappy Gall, that above Seven Years could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move; and the Licenſe of the Preſs, and the Eruption of the late accurſed Plot, furniſht me with an Opportunity, under the umbrage of a popular Champion, to wreak my own private Spight and Revenge. This I declare was the true Cauſe that miſled me into ſo much Spleen and Venome, of which I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily repent and am aſhamed, and humbly implore Pardon at the Feet of that Royal Prince for all thoſe accumulated wrongs I have done both againſt his Honour and Vertue: and from the bottom of my Soul I wiſh, as I have been the greateſt (I mean in my little capacity) ſo I may be the laſt of his Enemies.</p>
            <p>And truly my Faults, how criminal ſoever, are likewiſe ſo Univerſal, that I ſtand not alone under this convicting Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For too many, alas, and thoſe of the greateſt Men in <hi>England</hi> have my ſins too to anſwer for. For where the true Preſervation of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> makes One Patriot (as they call themſelves) Uneaſineſs, Diſguſt, or a Court-Grudg makes Twenty; whilſt <hi>Reformation</hi> is the leaſt buyſineſs of thoſe that moſt pretend to it. How many Perſons of the higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Kingdom (if they would be but half ſo ingenuous as
<pb facs="tcp:50755:3"/>I am) could tell you that tho' <hi>Religion</hi> and Property are the pretended Quarrel againſt the great Pilots above, their real Greivance is that their own Hands are not at the <hi>Rudder,</hi> and the State Helme is only Steerd awry, becauſe ſome happier ſome envied Court Darling ſits at it before them. Thus as poor <hi>Abel</hi> Dyed for being a greater Favourite to God then his Brother, the ſame Diſcontent that made <hi>Cain</hi> a Murderer, makes a great Man a Patriot.</p>
            <p>But now, tho' this plain Confeſſion, how diſadvantageous ſoever to my ſelf, might have been curtil'd into a ſomething more Excuſable Errour, by laying the whole blame on that more pardonable Folly of being miſtaken or ſeduced, yet I declare I had rather trebble my bluſhes, than fly to ſo mean a refuge as a Lye for any part of an Apology. And therefore I muſt own, though with the greater ſhame, I was ſo far from any Advice or Encouragement for the writing my firſt Libel, <hi>The Character of a Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> that I had finiſht it before ever I let it ſee Light: But then indeed I Coveted the Approbation of my Honourable <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet</hi> Patron, and entruſted a Friend to ſhew it him, who truly made but little Correction, onely he expreſt his Diſlike of one or two paſſages in it, and for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, <hi>Bid the Author ſpeak more favourably of Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now ſince the Malevolent ſpirit of <hi>Revenge</hi> was the fatal Luſt I gratified, and that foul Tempter the Plot roſe up to lend both Means and Opportunitie, I am reſolved, like a true pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent <hi>Debauch,</hi> to renounce both the <hi>Whore</hi> and the <hi>Bawd;</hi> and as I abhor the Sorcery of the Firſt, ſo loath the Lewdneſs of the Laſt: Lewdneſs indeed! for to all the looſe Deſires, and proſtitute Imaginations that <hi>Faction</hi> ever whored after Our late Plot has been the unhappy Pandar.</p>
            <p>What was it but the Plot that furniſht the world with ſo much counterfeit Zeal, and Gilded Hypocriſy, making the greateſt of Athieſts, the greateſt Stickler for Religion? What brought the moſt rigid Fanaticks to the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Communion and Sacrament to Capacitate them for an Office of Truſt; and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend the Throats of the greateſt true Proteſtant City Dons even to the Gorging of Perjury, but the Plot. What makes the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis independent of the Crown, and the lopping the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and borrowing the Militia to fight againſt Black Bills the Principal Expedient for the ſafety of the King and the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:50755:4"/>but the Plot? — What has ſet up ſo many City Poſts and Chains, to keep out <hi>Spaniſh Pilgrims,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Guards,</hi> but the Plot? — And riddle me riddle what made the whole Body of the Antipopiſh Diſſenters in their Higheſt Enmity and Dudgeon againſt Plots, and <hi>Rome,</hi> deſire to be united, and incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Popiſh Church of <hi>England,</hi> but the Plot? — What is it arraighns the Laws, Libells Courts, and Blackens Kings; ſupplies the poyſon'd Gall to all Republick Pens, prefers a <hi>Raree-Show</hi> before a <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and ſets a <hi>Milton</hi> above an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, but the Plot? The Plot writ the Aſſociation: and 'twas Plots Popiſh Plots too that inſtall'd the Covenant, Plots that pul'd down the Church to ſet up the Kirk, rays'd an Arbitrary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Wealth to pull down an Arbitrary Legal Monarchy, and cut off the Kings Head to make him Glorious? — What is it that Plots cannot or have not don though never ſo Romantick or Impoſſible? Have they not made a whole Proteſtant Church all Popiſh, and the Epiſcopal Clergy Tooth and Nayle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring for their own Deſtruction? Yes, and the Mildeſt and Beſt of Kings, after ſo moderate an Adminiſtration of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Raign of above <hi>Twenty</hi> quiet Halcyon years together, a Raign, where Law and Juſtice were never ſtretch unleſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Mercy and Indulgence, a Raign, where too eaſy Forgiveneſs, and receiving his pardon'd Enemies the warm ungrateful Snakes too near into the Boſom of Majeſty, and too high into his Truſt and Honours, has been the onely fault in the Throne; This very Godlike Tempred King after ſo long a Harmony of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in ſo calm a Sphear of Glory, by the all-aſperſing Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel of a Plot, ſhall nevertheleſs all of a ſuddain throw his long golden Reins away, and to bring in that unweildy Leviathan Arbitrary Power involve his Gray Haires in inextricable Broyl and Tumult, looſe all the peaceful Reſt of Age, and all to turn a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> a <hi>Jehu,</hi> a <hi>Phaeton</hi> even in the laſt Race of his Life. Nay and to make the Hideous Fantom a little more Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantick, this very Prince (if Noyſe and Plots may be beleiv'd) ſhall be penſioning and confederating with <hi>France,</hi> though againſt himſelf, to the betraying of his Crown and Empire.</p>
            <p>But Popery and Arbitrary Power are to be brought in; and though by Head and Shoulders, though by the moſt Ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Means, as wide from Senſe and Truth as North from South, 'tis all alike. 'Tis but inſinuating into the Brainleſs
<pb facs="tcp:50755:4"/>heads of the People that the King himſelf (as I told you) is leaguing with <hi>France</hi> to bring in the Pope: and though the <hi>French</hi> King has his Sword in the very Bowels of <hi>Flanders,</hi> againſt the Faithfulleſt Son of <hi>Rome</hi> the King of <hi>Spain;</hi> though he can ſcarce keep his profane hands even from <hi>Italy,</hi> the Seat of the Roman God himſelf; though he has pyrated the very beſt Flower in the Popes Garden the Regalias of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and ſhaken the very Papal Supremacy, even to the pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down of that dreadful Curſe of Excommunication, had the Pope but Courage to pronounce it; nay though he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted the Proteſtant Rebellion in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and brought the very Turk into Chriſtendom, poſſibly not many years journey from the very Gates of <hi>Rome;</hi> yet all this while this very King of <hi>France</hi> ſhall be the Popes right Hand, his Spear, his Shield, his every thing, and is ſetting up the Romiſh Intereſt with all the Induſtry and Vigour in the World: And to compleat this Mountainous Monſter of a Conſpiracy, the King and Court of England (for Plots and Popery make all things go down) ſhall be as deep in it as He. And though, God knows, there is not ſo much as the leaſt Signe Appearance or ſhadow of any thing of this, and the Infuſers of all this poyſon into the unreaſoning Multitude are conſcious 'tis all rank Forgery, no matter for that: They know whom they have to deal with, the Headlong Mobile of <hi>England,</hi> a People of that ſtrange Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, that they fear nothing that they <hi>See,</hi> but all things that they <hi>Hear.</hi> And thoſe very men that in Viſible dangers ſhall face the Mouths of Cannons, yet at the Apprehenſion of Caſtles in the Ayre, Popery and Arbitrary Power, from the Imaginary Thunderbolts from that quarter ſhall ſtart like Hinds. 'Tis but winding that Horne, and they fall as flat before the ſound as the Walls of <hi>Jericho;</hi> and nothing but breathing the Spirit of <hi>Rebellion</hi> into them, can rowze them out of the fright on't. And who at laſt are the Great Firſt Movers in all theſe National Enflamings? — Truly thoſe very Men that bawld lowdeſt for the Preſervation of His Majeſties Perſon, againſt Plots and Popiſh Swords, are the Numerical Perſons that Scandalize His Majeſty with Popiſhly affected, to the withdrawing the hearts of his Subjects, which are his greateſt and ſtrongeſt Guard againſt all Plots or Swords whatſoever. And whilſt this Zeal for the King and the Government Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht,
<pb facs="tcp:50755:5"/>brings theſe mighty leading Nimrods into the Chace, 'tis much to be feared the Cry of running down Popery, is more to call the Hunters together then the Game intended.</p>
            <p>Thus ſince the Plot is made the Tool for all this Miſchief, and furniſhes all the Fuel for Diſſentions and Diſcords the great Incendiaries of the World; I am reſolved to bid adieu to it: and to leave it as I found it, draw the true Picture of that Wonderworking Prodigy that has ſo long and ſo highly (to aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment be it ſpoken) put three Kingdoms into a Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And now, Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi> having ſhaken hands with that troubleſom Companion Whiggiſm; my Converſion, as the Divines ſay of Chriſtianity, makes me happy, if but in the very Eaſe of Mind it gives me, and the Slavery it rids me of; A <hi>Whigg</hi> being that Owlight ſort of Animal that, unleſs in a Coach and ſix, it never looks abroad without being hooted at. And I thank my Starrs I ſhall now be no longer confined but to two perches in a Cage, like the <hi>Salamanca</hi> Doctor, juſt to hop to <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Coffee-Houſe and then home again; But once more venture to walk by Daylight, and from this time forward look Senſe and Quality in the Face, and inſtead of Shades and Coverts returne to Converſation and the World again; And that I may no wayes forfeit thoſe good Graces that, Sir, from your ſelf and all other Perſons of Honour and Loyalty I ſhall ever am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly Covet, and ſtudy to preſerue: I ſhall fully and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely abjure all Turbulence and Malignity whatever; and to avoyd the Crime and Fate of <hi>Saphira</hi> retain no one part of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repented ſins about me, that might make my whole Atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Sacrifice unacceptable; but perſevere with that Integrity and Honeſty that may render me ſo much the more worthy to ſubſcribe my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt Obedient and moſt Humble Servant. <hi>E. Settle.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="narrative">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50755:5"/>
            <head>A Narrative, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Year 78 it pleaſed thoſe Powers that inſpir'd them to raiſe up Mr. <hi>Oats, Bedlows, Dugdale, Prance,</hi> &amp;c. to be the Preſervers (or what properer name, you'l give 'em) of the King and three Kingdoms, from the Malice and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations of the Papiſts; who by an ample Diſcovery (whether given us by the right or left hand of Providence it matters not) came enlightned by Repentance, and animated by Zeal, or ſomething as active, to betray their old Colleagues and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons the Papiſts, and Jeſuits, and by detecting Crimes ineffable, and Plots inſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to give the World that unknown ſcene of Villany, and the moſt unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Myſtery of Iniquity, that ever Mankind was aſtoniſht to hear, or puzled to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thom. And that this Plot is more remarkable, than all that <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> Conclaves or Devils ever managed before, it has ſo many croſs Windings Turnings and Mazes throughout, that whatever Wit, Prudence, or Conduct, thoſe Great and Politick Enemies of our Religion have ever been Maſters of in former intrigues; in this only Plot We have a Cabal of ſuch extravagant Fools, and Madmen, as Hiſtory affords no Parrallel of.</p>
            <p>The Converſion and Subjection of Great Brittain to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion and Power, after ſo long, and almoſt total a Revolt from <hi>Rome,</hi> is, or ought to be (and the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> muſt be Senſible as much) a Work of that politick undertaking, that requires the wiſeſt and Subtleſt ſteps, that the mightieſt Machiavels of all Ages ever moved in; and yet through the whole carrying on of this Conſpiracy, the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> and their Adhoerents took ſuch indirect meaſures and oppoſite Means to obtain their great Ends, that there is not ſo much as the Shadow of right reaſon, or ſcarce common ſenſe in the whole management. The buſineſs therefore of this following diſcourſe, is to manifeſt what an unthinking pack of <hi>Jehues</hi> the Papiſts have been through the whole Plot, and what Lunacy and Infatuations drove 'em; with the particular account of what Snares and Nets they had provided againſt us, and what Cobweb Lawn they and the Diſcoverers have made 'em of.</p>
            <p>Firſt then for their killing of the King.</p>
            <p>This dire undertaking being the great Wheel that was to ſet the whole Machine a working, the Papiſts by virtue of a Summons from father Whitebread, beld a General Conſult at the White-horſe Tavern in the <hi>Strand,</hi> at which were preſent Father <hi>Warren</hi> Rector of Liege, Sr. <hi>Thomas Preſton</hi> Baronet, Father <hi>Marſh</hi> Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of <hi>Ghent,</hi> Father <hi>Willams</hi> Rector of <hi>Watten,</hi> Sr. John <hi>Warner,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Oats</hi> Nar. par. XXVIII.</note> and Sr. Robert <hi>Brett</hi> Baronets, Father <hi>Poole,</hi> Edmond <hi>Nevil, &amp;c.</hi> who together with Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> came over Sea upon the ſaid ſummons, and met the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fathers at the ſaid Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, in all to the number of fifty <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> on <hi>April</hi> the 24th, 78.</p>
            <p>Where after long and ſerious debate, the great Reſolve of this general Conſult, <hi>was, that</hi> Pickering <hi>and</hi> Groves <hi>ſhould go on in their attempt to aſſaſſinate the Kings Perſon, for which the firſt ſhould have</hi> 30000 <hi>Maſſes ſaid, for the health of his Soul, and the other</hi> 1500. <hi>l. which Reſolve they all Conſented, and Signed to,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> carryed it from Conſult to Conſult, and Chamber to Chamber to get all their hands ſubſcribed to it.</p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Groves</hi> were two blind Gunners, that had followed the King for ſeveral years for the ſame Murdering Deſign, but ineffectually. <hi>Pickering</hi> as <hi>Bedlow</hi> affirm's, <hi>haveing had ſeveral fair opportunities, but miſcarried. One time the flint of his Piſtol was looſe, another time there was no Powder in the pan, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time he had charged with all Bullets, and no Powder. for which Miſdemeanors he received</hi> 20 <hi>Laſhes of Diſcipline.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tryal. p. 24.</note> But his Comrade <hi>Groves</hi> for ought we know never charged his Gun at all, for we neither read of his having any opportunities or hitting or Miſſing.</p>
            <p>Here is to be obſerved the great Depth and Wiſdome of this grand Conſult of no leſs then 50 Polititians, Theſe <hi>Popiſh</hi> Conſpirators, that (as it appears,) had been for ſeveral years together, at Piſtolling the King, by the hands of theſe two
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50755:6"/>heroick blood-thirſters are at the charge and trouble of coming from ſeveral parts beyond Sea: and the great Reſult of that famous Aſſembly is, that theſe two a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Wretches, a brace of fumbling fools, that had been ſo many years ſo auk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly about it before, ſhould ſtil be continued and Employed for the great work of murdering the King, without ſo much as the leaſt propoſition of one wiſer head, or better Marksman to come in for a ſnack with them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irelands</hi> Tryal p 22.</note> For the greater Sons of Thunder, ſuch as the four Gentlemen <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ruffians, were not thought on till the <hi>Auguſt</hi> following, and in the ſame month <hi>Conyers</hi> and <hi>Anderſon</hi> ſtrook in with their Leaguer Cloaks, and broad Daggers for the Kings <hi>New-market</hi> walk: nor was Sr. George <hi>Wakeman</hi> treated with, till the <hi>July</hi> after this Conſult; beſides Sr. George <hi>Wakeman</hi> could be ingaged in the Murder without the trouble of any ſuch general.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irelands</hi> Tryal p. 21.</note> Aſſembly: a letter from <hi>Whitebread</hi> then at St. <hi>Omers</hi> being ſufficient authority to propoſe 10000. l. and embarque ſo great a Man in the deſign without any For reign Summons for general Conſults, conveying Reſolves to be Sign'd, or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing of hands either for his Poiſoning,<note place="margin">Nart. par. XXXIII.</note> Conyers Stabbing, or the four Ruffians Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
            <p>But tho this <hi>April</hi> Subſcribing to that very Decree, that belike had been their Act and deed of ſo many Years before, is ſomewhat Oddiſh, yet this great hinge of <hi>April</hi> Conſult is almoſt all the whole Plot to move upon: and tho the <hi>Jeſuites, Pickering's</hi> Elder Brothers, for no wiſer a Reſolve at ſo vaſt a Meeting deſerved as many Laſhes as he. yet I aſſure you, and the Doctor ſhall ſwear it, it was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary, that <hi>Whitebread</hi> and the reſt ſhould Subſcribe in <hi>April</hi> 78. that they might be hang'd for't in <hi>June</hi> 79.</p>
            <p>But before the Reader proceed's, he is requeſted not to be ſtartled at Inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence Abſurdities Contradictions, or indeed Impoſſibilities. For a Plot's nothing without 'em. For example, he'l find in the unerring Drs Depoſitions, that the Dr. read a Pacquet at St. <hi>Omers</hi> directed from <hi>Whitebread</hi> to <hi>Aſhby,</hi> where amongſt other matters we meet theſe Numerical words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the pacquet was contained an accompt of one</hi> Pickering, <hi>that waits upon the Jeſuites at</hi> Sommerſet-houſe, <hi>to ſhoot the King as he was walking in</hi> St. James's Park <hi>when he was at ſome diſtance from his Nobles and Attendants, but the flint of his Piſtol being ſomewhat looſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nar. Par. XIX</note> 
               <hi>he did defer the action till another opportunity, and if he had done it, and had ſuffer'd, he ſhould have had</hi> 30000 <hi>Maſſes for the health of his Soul</hi> ['tis well he tells 'em what reward he was to have had; for poſſibly the firſt deſign upon the Kings Life might have been made without a general Conſult, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they might be ignorant at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> either of the Man or the Bargain; or elſe it might be ſo long ſince they ſet him at Work, that they might have forgotten it] <hi>But theſe Letters were Signed by</hi> Thomas White alias Whitebread; <hi>which Letters when read, the Fathers in the Engliſh Seminary were in great trouble for the negligence of the ſaid</hi> Pickering; and the <hi>Deponent ſaw and read them in the latter part of</hi> January &amp;c. And that we may be aſſured <hi>January</hi> was the Month, the next Paragraph in the Narrative is the Subject of the Dr, and his Confeſſors diſcourſe about keeping the Kings Martyrdom Day.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this invincible demonſtration of <hi>Januaries</hi> Packet: The Dr. upon Oath before the Houſe of Lords, aſſures us,<note place="margin">Journal 29. Nov. 78.</note> that this Attempt and failing of <hi>Pickerings</hi> Gun was ſome few days before the Conſult in <hi>April.</hi> And more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly at <hi>Pickerings</hi> Tryal he aſcertains the expreſs time to be in <hi>March,</hi> being askt.<note place="margin">Tryal p. 24.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sir Ch. L. <hi>Do you know any thing of</hi> Pickerings <hi>doing pennance, and for what?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oats. <hi>Yes my Lord in the Month of</hi> March <hi>laſt (for theſe perſons have followed the King ſeveral Years) but he at that time had not look't to the flint of his Piſtol, but it was looſe, and he durſt not Venture to give Fire, he had a fair opportunity as</hi> Whitebread <hi>ſaid, and becauſe he miſt it through his own negligence he underwent Pennance, and had</hi> 20 <hi>ſtrokes of Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now can any thing in Nature be more ſtrange, than that <hi>Whitebread</hi> ſhould ſend the St. <hi>Omers</hi> Fathers in <hi>January,</hi> a perfect Relation of a crime not committed till the <hi>March</hi> following; Well but that the <hi>Devil</hi> and the <hi>Pope</hi> are ſworn Friends, and Conjuration may do much, otherwiſe ſome fooliſh unbelievers would not ſtick
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50755:6"/>to call it a downright Elliotiſm. But alas to confute that Error, we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that the confinement to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Time,</hi> or <hi>Place</hi> or any of thoſe circumſtantial Popperies are a formality fitt for a Country Aſſizes, or an Evidence againſt a poor Sheep Stealer or ſo. But againſt that terrible thing called a Kingkiller, and ſuch a <hi>Goliah</hi> Traytor as <hi>Pickring,</hi> ſo mean a Tongue-tye had been much too humble and ſervil an impoſition for the High and Mighty Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> the Saviour of no leſs then three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>And to ſhow you that this Figurative way of ſpeaking is an Elegance, that the Dr. extreamly Prides himſelf in, you ſhall have it from one end of the Plot to the other. For another inſtance at this very conſult in his Narative,<note place="margin">Tryal p. 28.</note> and at <hi>Pickerings</hi> Trial the Aſſembly conſiſted of fifty Jeſuites: but at <hi>Langhorns</hi> Trial, becauſe 'twas proved there was never a Room at the White-horſe Tavern that would hold above a dozen People, then the aforeſaid fifty upon ſecond thoughts were dwin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into eighteen or twenty, and thoſe in ſeveral Rooms.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Langhorns</hi> Tryal p. 47.</note> And therefore as I ſaid before ſince 'twas inconſiſtent with the Glory of ſo Sacred a Deliverer to be ſo poorly confined; <hi>January</hi> and <hi>March</hi> in his Kalendar, and fifty or twenty in his Arithmetick ſhall be all alike. Whilſt he ſcorns his Diſcovery ſhould be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by Vulgar Capacities, and therefore like a ſecond Revelation has wrapt it in Riddle and Miſtery.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Reader is humbly deſired not to be puzled to imagine how Mr. <hi>Picker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſhould preſent a Gun (between a Piſtol and a Carbine) twice at the King, which one time for want of Prime, and another by being Charg'd with all Bullets would not go off, and yet not be apprehended or ſo much as ſeen by any one of all the Kings Attendance, and that too in ſo publick and open a place as St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park,</hi> a place where there is not ſo much as a Bramble or Bryar or any one Covert throughout it enough to Shrowd a Pigmey, much leſs two Manſlayers; excepting the Oſiers within the Canal (but thoſe are moated round and therefore inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſible) neither would I have the Reader ſurpris'd at Armies of Pilgrims and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Black Bills, and other Miraculous Tooles uſed in the Popiſh Service: for let me tell you, Time was, that is in the firſt year of the Doctors Reign, rather then ſuch a Bloody Aſſaſſin as <hi>Pickering</hi> ſhould have wanted convenience for ſo Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable a Deſign, the Doctor if occaſion had been, could have concealed him in a Miſty Cloack, or have Conjur'd up a Buſh to hide him in, like a ſecond <hi>Jonas Goad,</hi> that ſhould have grown up one day, and withered down the next; beſides rather then the Pilgrims ſhould have wanted Strength for the Work in hand, he ſhould have made 'em all Gyants at leaſt, nay and if that would not have done, before the Maſſacre ſhould have went lame, or the Proteſtants have wanted Cutthroats he ſhould have brought you half <hi>Ovid's Metamorphoſis</hi> into the Plot, and have marcht ye an Army of <hi>Satyrs</hi> and <hi>Centaurs</hi> through <hi>Cheapſide.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now after the Kings being beſett all round like the Man in the Almanack with ſo many Piſtols Ponyards Swords and poyſons; after the Iſſue and Succeſs of all this dead doing Artillery the next great movement of the Plot was, when the King had had the preheminence of having his Cutt firſt, the Proteſtants Throats were to have been Cutt next.</p>
            <p>For doing of which we have the Drs. Liſt of Officers for the raiſing of an Army of which the Lord <hi>Belaſis</hi> was to be Lord General, Lord <hi>Petres</hi> Leiftenant General Sir. <hi>Thomas Ratcliff</hi> Major General, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and their Patents or Commiſſions were Signed by the General of the Jeſuits <hi>Johannes Paulus d' Oliva,</hi> And particularly Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> Swears before the Lord Ch. Juſtice <hi>Scroggs, Oct.</hi> 24.<note place="margin">Nar. p. 58.</note> that he ſaw the Lord <hi>Bellaſis</hi> Letter to <hi>Fenwick</hi> in the month of <hi>July</hi> 78. to accknowledge the receipt of his Commiſſion, and in <hi>May</hi> 78. he ſaw the Commiſſion for the Lord <hi>Petres</hi> in the hands of Mr. <hi>Langhorn,</hi> and another in <hi>July</hi> to make Sr. <hi>George Wakeman</hi> Phyſitian to the Army; and for the inferiour Commiſſions Stampt and Sealed by <hi>Whitebread</hi> he himſelf in theſe very months delivered ſeveral of them with his own hand.</p>
            <p>This Army being to be fixt for ſtriking immediately upon the Kings falling, was conſequently to be all Liſted and Arm'd in the Kings Life time, and all <hi>incognito</hi> in a Proteſtant Kingdom, and upon having none but ſuch notoriouſly known Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50755:7"/>for the Commanders, it was Morally impoſible to have drawn in any other Malecontents into the Confederacy: Beſides the very propoſal of liſting any of the Proteſtants had been the way to have Diſcovered the Conſpiracy and Ruin'd all: and therefore the whole Body of this Army muſt neceſſarily have conſiſted of all Papiſts; and if the Jeſuites were ſo cockſure of the Strength, and Courage of the Popiſh party in <hi>England</hi> to think 'm able to give a tug for the Popes Reſtauration <hi>Vi et armis</hi> with open Hoſtility againſt all the Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> they muſt certainly be inſpired with no common Enthuſiaſms, and take their Leaders for no leſs then <hi>Saul</hi>'s and <hi>David</hi>'s, expecting to ſee 'm return fluſht with ſo wondrous a Succeſs that the very Daughters of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould meet 'm with Songs and Timbrels, and give them no leſs a Welcome then <hi>Petres</hi> has Slain his thouſands and <hi>Bellaſis</hi> his ten thouſand.</p>
            <p>But no matter this is but one Drs. Opinion. Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> and his Jeſuits were for doing the Work with Popiſh Generals and Popiſh Armies, but Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> is of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mind, and he and his Jeſuits were for quite another ſort of conduct. Tis true he concurrs with Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> that the King was to fall by as many pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate hands as the Dr. pleas'd, but then to ſubdue the reſt of the Kingdom. (Lord have mercy upon us) a Maſſacre was to enſue. And becauſe he and his Plotters were not altogether ſo Strong in Faith as Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> his, and believed the Popiſh party to be too Small and therefore too Weak of themſelves alone to go thorough ſtich with ſo great an Undertaking, they had found this expedient, <hi>Viz. They had deſign'd</hi> (he tells you) <hi>to fling the Murder of the King upon the King killing Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians and then to engage the Epiſcopal party to riſe with the Papiſts in revenge of the Kings blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> p. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and cut the Fanatick's throats; and when with their help they had deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed the Fanatical party, and weakened the Kingdom by ſo univerſal a Blow, then they had decreed to turn their Swords all of a ſudden againſt the hearts of their Colleagues the Epiſcopals;</hi> and ſo playing the ſubtle <hi>Polyphemus,</hi> and reſerving them for the laſt morſel, when they had no other Enemies left, by this laſt dexterous Wheel about, and cutting the Epiſcopal Proteſtant Throats too, the great Work of Projection had been Compleated, and the Papiſts left Maſters of the Field, whilſt <hi>Jó</hi> by <hi>Faean Jo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Triumphum England</hi> was there own. Here we find Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> his Meaſures quite broken, for alas this Maſſacre of <hi>Dugdals</hi> is of a quite different piece with <hi>Oats</hi> his Batalia: but no matter more ways than one to the Wood, and neither falſe Scents nor hunting Counter ſpoils the ſport either in Plotters or Diſcoverers.</p>
            <p>But methinks, this laſt ſtratagem of Mr. <hi>Dugdales,</hi> is the oddeſt fancied out-of-the-way project that ever Folly or Frenzy invented, for ſuppoſe the bloody mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Pickering</hi> had learnt to charge his Gun the right way, with ſome Powder, and not all Bullets, and let us imagine that after his late diſcipline upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he had mended his aim, and had Kill'd the King. How muſt the Epiſcopal Party be poſſeſt it was done by a Presbyterian hand, for it was impoſſible the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its ſhould ever expect, that a ſingle Aſſaſſinate in ſuch a place as St. <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Park</hi> in the Face of the Court, and approaching ſo near as within Piſtol ſhot, upon the Murther of the King ſhould ever eſcape ſeizing, either by the hands of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or His Majeſties Servants that always attended him. Upon this Conſequence how muſt the Papiſts, I ſay ſteer to draw in the Epiſcopal Party to the Maſſacre, muſt they give it out it was done by a Presbyterian hand, and thereupon hand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver head without any Examination, but right or wrong the Epiſcopals upon the meer motives of a Hearſay ſhould <hi>Pellmel</hi> fall to butchering perhaps one third of the Nation. This Preſumption in the Jeſuits is ſuch an impudent Piece of Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as certainly was never matcht, it being ſo far from the Principles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that nothing but Lunacy it ſelf could ſuſpect them guilty of ſo brutal nay ſo execrable a Thought. But ſuppoſe this Maſſacre was not to commence till <hi>Pickering</hi> had been taken, Examined and Tryed for the Fact, and let us for once imagine further, that they had before hand inſtructed him to own himſelf a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick, and reſolutely and impudently even at the Gallows dye a Sectary, and lay the crime upon the Diſſenters; yet never did the Jeſuits ſo fam'd for Politicks go ſo ſenſleſly to work, as here, firſt not only to chooſe ſo ſhallow a headpiece as <hi>Pickerings</hi> for ſuch a Maſterpiece of Cheat and Villany, and ſo known a Popiſh Face
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50755:7"/>as his too a Lay Brother, and Candleſnuffer of the Queens Chappel to diſguiſe for a Presbyterian. So that here upon the upſhot of <hi>Pickerings</hi> being diſcovered (or indeed any other of the <hi>Ruffians</hi>) as none but Fools could think otherwiſe, if they had believed the Church of <hi>England</hi> of that Maſſacring Spirit (as belike they did) had they been in their right Wits, they ought rather to have feared to have had the Maſſacre on their own ſide, and their own Throats, not the Fanaticks have paid for 't. Theſe are the Tribe of the Jeſuits, and this the Plot the Dr. aſſures us had been hatching ever ſince King <hi>James</hi> his days, yet we ſee after no leſs than almoſt a Hundred years Labor, what the Mountain brings forth, and after ſo much Intrigue and ſuch indefatigable Pains, how ſillily and awkwardly at laſt theſe Matchiav ils put their Noddles together.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding this movement of <hi>Dugdales,</hi> does not extreamly well cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton with Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s, yet that Diſcoverers like good Wits may ſometimes Jump, Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> is for an Army too; for after the laying the Death of the King on the Presbyterians, and ingaging the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the Maſſacre, he ſays in theſe words. <hi>And then my Lord there was to be a Maſſacre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">the Jeſ. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi> pag. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and if any did eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape</hi> (<hi>viz</hi> the Maſſacre) <hi>that they could not be ſure were Papiſts, they were to have an Army to cut them off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that here was an Army in <hi>Embrio,</hi> tho not ſo early raiſed as to do the Drs. Execution; for alas here it is plain, that the Maſſacre was to come firſt and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my laſt, to cut off the Remains of what had eſcap'd the Maſſacre, the Maſſacre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuppoſed to be performed by down right Bear-garden play, with a helter skel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Aſſaſſinates with Quarter ſtaffs, black Bills, Spits, Pole-axes, or any other Weapon that came next to hand, and the ſucceeding Army was only to be enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Reer of the Catholick Cauſe, the greateſt part of the <hi>Brunt</hi> being over before the Army came into play. Here 'tis true that the Lord <hi>Bellaſis,</hi> and the reſt of the Right Honorable Commanders had entred the liſts; but alas, only to attaque thoſe ſcattered remnants that had eſcaped. This Diſpenſation of Affairs at <hi>Rome</hi> would appear an Indignity to Perſons of the L. <hi>Bellaſis, Petres</hi> and <hi>Powis</hi> Quality and Eſtates: but we are to Conſider 'twas the <hi>Popes</hi> pleaſure, and no Poſt too mean even for Princes and Potentates in the Catholick Battles.</p>
            <p>But here the Aſtoniſh't Reader muſt make a litle pauſe and ſtand amaz'd at the unprecedented Cruelty of all Popiſh Miſcreants: It was not enough belike for 'em to make a Maſſacre of the Proteſtants throughout the Kingdom, and mow down the Hereticks with ſo univerſal a blow, but after all this an Army too muſt be raiſed to deſtroy even the very Gleanings of the Field. Never certainly had been ſo in humane a Scene of Butchery, when after no leſs then a Maſſacre, all that were not known Papiſts that had Eſcaped were to periſh likewiſe; inſomuch that by this Depopulation of Root and Brance, not ſo much as a heretick Hewer of wood or Drawer of Water had been left unſlaughter'd.</p>
            <p>Now after this damnable Popiſh Decree, and all this Lamentable Tragedy, I admire what need the Pope had in his long Bull read by Dr. Oats in <hi>Blundels</hi> hands after the diſpoſal of Biſhopricks,<note place="margin">Nar. p. 72.</note> Abbotſhips &amp;c. <hi>for want of Engliſh born Preiſts enough for all the dignities of the Church of England to decree ſuch and ſuch Spaniards, and other forreigners ſhould ſupply that want, and order ſuch and ſuch for reading Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and Divinity in all great Towns and Colledges, and ſuch and ſuch to be employed in Preaching, catechizing, and aſſiſting at the Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas and welladay, after ſo Numberleſs an Aſſaſſination as All the Proteſtants in <hi>England,</hi> there would have been ſo little Occaſion for Supplies of <hi>Spaniſh</hi> prieſts, that there would ſcarce have been Flock enough left to overſtock the very St. <hi>Omers</hi> Brotherhood. Many a great Town in <hi>England</hi> would have ſtood in ſo little need of a Philoſophy or Divinity School, that there would not have been ſo much as three ſouls left alive in't: and three Surviving Families had been more then many a nine Pariſhes in <hi>England</hi> could have produced, That the <hi>Pope</hi> (one would think) might have Spared his untimely proviſion for his Underchurches, for unleſs his Jagoe Pilgrims and other kind Viſitants had repeopled the Kingdom, the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derchurches might have e'en ſtood Idle, and the very Cathedral alone in many a fair Town have held the Congregation of the whole County.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:50755:8"/>Beſides in my Mind 'twas mighty ridiculous in the Plotters to trouble their heads about the Succeſſion, and (as the Dr. tells you) <hi>to threaten the Duke if he followed his Brothers ſteps to ſend him after him.</hi> For truly when Mr. <hi>Dugdales</hi> Maſſacres and Armies had left him no Subjects living but Papiſts, 'twas not three Farthings matter what the Succeſſors Religion was, nor was it likely he could ever follow his Brothers ſteps and favor the Proteſtants, when he had not one Proteſtant left to favor.</p>
            <p>But now after all this diſmal, and deplorable buſineſs, methinks, I cannot make a livelier Repreſentation of the woful ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> than by fancying I ſee the diſtreſt and deſolate <hi>Britannia,</hi> mourning o're her ſlaughter'd Sons, like the <hi>Brent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Kings howling over <hi>Lardella</hi>'s Coffin. But now what if by a new turn of State <hi>Lardella</hi> ſhould be alive at laſt, and maugre this fatal and univerſal Doom, ſeveral Thouſands of thoſe Sentenced Hereticks ſhould live many a fair Summers day after it. And that all this is undeniable truth, we have no leſs then Mr. <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low's</hi> Reprieve to ſave them: for after his landing <hi>an Army of</hi> 10000 <hi>Men from</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>at</hi> Bradlington Bay <hi>to ſurprize</hi> Hull <hi>Garriſon, and the Lord</hi> Petre <hi>and</hi> Powis <hi>having another Army to march to</hi> Pembrookſhire, <hi>to meet a Third Army of</hi> 20 <hi>or</hi> 30000 <hi>Men, who were to land at Milford haven, being an Army compoſed of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Men and Pilgrims from St.</hi> Jago <hi>in</hi> Spain,<note place="margin">Lords Journ. 12th day of Nov. 78.</note> 
               <hi>and whatever ſhould happen that their Strength, as they ſaid, might be ſufficient, they had</hi> 40000 <hi>Men</hi> (a Fourth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) <hi>ready in</hi> London, <hi>beſides thoſe that would on the Alarm be poſted at Every Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe door, to have Kill'd the Soldiers, as they came out of their quarters,</hi> which I ſuppoſe at leaſt muſt make a fifth Army more, beſides a ſixth Army of Mr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s from <hi>France,</hi> expreſly to have been let in upon the Kings death, but at preſent forgotten by Mr. <hi>Bedlow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Irelands</hi> Tryal p. 29.</note> Now amongſt all theſe formidable Armies to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by <hi>Bellaſis, Petres, Powis &amp;c.</hi> The edge of Mr. <hi>Dugdales</hi> Maſſacre is a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle rebated: for here, as <hi>Bedlow</hi> tells the Houſe of Lords, <hi>after</hi> Conyers <hi>had kill'd the King,</hi> Keins <hi>the Duke of</hi> Monmouth, Pritchard <hi>the Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>Mr.</hi> Right <hi>my Lord</hi> Shaftesbury, <hi>Mr.</hi> O neal <hi>my Lord</hi> Oſſory, <hi>and one whoſe name he had forgotten the Duke of</hi> Ormond; <hi>after all theſe Perſons were kill'd, the Papiſts did not queſtion the Power of the reſt, or their Counſels, but that they ſhould out do them; for they would give ſuch great Pay, that all ſorts of Malecontents, and People that depended on their fortune,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lords Journ. <hi>ibid</hi> 12th of N.</note> 
               <hi>would be ready to ſerve them.</hi> All this perform'd, (as he tells you afterward, <hi>they deſigned to eſtabliſh their Government ſecure enough, for they intended utterly to extinguiſh all ſorts of People, that would not really be converted to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and to prove it, perſecute their neareſt Relations that were Obſtinate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we have the abovenamed Lords Generals a little more honorably employ'd under Mr. <hi>Bedlows</hi> Banners, than Mr. <hi>Dugdales,</hi> the whole Glory of the Day being now like to be theirs, and not only Mr. <hi>Dugdales</hi> Presbyterians, that were to be Maſſacred by a medley of Papiſts, and Epiſcopals, manifeſtly reſcued from deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but they and all other Malecontents to be bribed into the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Army, and <hi>vice versâ</hi> make a part of the Catholick Forces to cut the Epiſcopal Throats. Here tho all the Proteſtants at long run were to be extinguiſht, yet the ſtream is not half ſo rapid as Mr. <hi>Dugdales;</hi> for here the Hereticks had time to cry Quarter, and have the fair Proffer of Converſion for their Deliverance, whilſt the deſtruction of the Obſtinate was only to approach by the ſlower hand of Perſecution.</p>
            <p>Thus far I have ſhowed you the many and wonderful Windings and Turnings of <hi>French</hi> Armies, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Armies, <hi>Flandrian</hi> Armies, and <hi>Pilgrim</hi> Armies and all the reſt of the Plot Forces, that were to deſtroy the King, Subvert the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Religion, and Subject the whole Nation to ſlavery and Popery. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all theſe manifold and various Motions of ſo many Armies for the Proteſtant Deſtruction, (as Bays his whiſpering Conſpirators wiſely obſerved of the two <hi>Brent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Kings: <hi>viz. When they heard us whiſper, 2dly. What they heard us whiſper, and laſtly whither they heard us at all or no.</hi>) So likewiſe in our Conſpiracy after we have given you an account by <hi>What</hi> Armies and <hi>When</hi> this great Deſign was to have been accompliſht, what if we come to <hi>Bays</hi> his laſt point, and prove the Work was to have been done by <hi>no Armies</hi> at all. I, that would be a Rarity indeed, and an Atchievement enough to immortalize the Policy and Glory of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50755:8"/>Well! As wondrous as this Atchievement may look, it is no more ſtrange than 'tis true. And that too as ſhall be manifeſtly made out by the cleareſt Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through the whole diſcovery. For Example Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> ſwears (as you have been told before) that <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Grove</hi> by the Jeſuits order, had been at Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the King the <hi>March</hi> before the <hi>April</hi> Conſult, and not only then but ſeveral Years before had been dogging the King, for the ſame Murdering purpoſe: nay upon further Examination we may track the Plot upon occaſions, even to the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>London.</hi> Here it viſibly appears, that many Years before the <hi>April</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the Deſign was Ripe for Execution, and the King for Falling, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Subverſion of the Government, and deſtruction of the Proteſtants that were always to attend it, muſt neceſſarily and inſeparably have Succeeded his Murder. This granted, and that upon further Inquiry we find the Commiſſions for the Army to be rais'd in <hi>England,</hi> not ſo much as delivered out till the Months of <hi>May, June, July, Auguſt</hi> 78. and the Forreign Armies from <hi>Jago, Flanders</hi> &amp;c. Expreſly to come over to joyn the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Forces, under the Command of <hi>Bellaſis, Petres, Powis</hi> &amp;c. Which Joyning of Armies Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> aſſures us was juſt ready to put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">Lords Journ. 12th. Nov. 78.</note> when the Deſign againſt the Kings Perſon was diſcovered. Beſides when <hi>Pickerings</hi> Gun Miſcarried in <hi>January,</hi> or at any time <hi>Winter</hi> or <hi>Summer,</hi> for all thoſe Years that <hi>Pickering</hi> followed the King, it was morally impoſſible, for either the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King to have always Armies ready to March, and Navies to Land them: ſo that upon the whole 'tis unanſwerably Evident that the ſtroke was to have been given without the leaſt Limb of any Army whatſoever, either For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign or Domeſtick.</p>
            <p>Upon theſe undeniable Demonſtrations mark the prodigious Proweſs, Strength and Courage of the Sons of <hi>Rome.</hi> Here to follow their firſt Blow, <hi>viz.</hi> the Kings Murder, muſt the Popiſh hands in England without any aſſiſtance whatever have made a Maſſacre, and to have kept their ground, either Killd, or Subjected the whole Body of the Proteſtants throughout the Kingdom. Alas! What were the Fooliſh inſignificant <hi>Iriſh, Piedmont,</hi> and <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacres compared to This? There the Religion of the Countries, was Popiſh, the Strength and Government Popiſh, and the Majority of lhe Peoqle all Papiſts, and what with the help of Surpriſe their Strength and advantages treble to thoſe of their unarmed Enemies. But the State of <hi>England</hi> has quite another Face; here the Strength, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Nation, is in Proteſtants hands, and upon ſeveral Scrutinies made of the number of the Papiſts throughout all <hi>England,</hi> upon Computation they are not found to be the hundred and fiftieth part of the Nation. So that as the Old poor Groveling Cutthroats in their ignobler Enterprizes went on with thoſe coward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encouragements of <hi>Hope, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Poſſibility</hi> on their ſide, The bolder <hi>Engliſh</hi> High-flyers lay all theſe duller inglorious trifles aſide, reſolved to aſſume the Souls and Strength of <hi>Hercules,</hi> each Man an <hi>Almanzor,</hi> or Couſin German to him at leaſt, whilſt the vaſt Bulk of a Hundred and Fifty to one odds had been to have faln, no doubt like a ſecond <hi>Goliah,</hi> with the ſtrength of a Pebble from a Roman hand.</p>
            <p>So that, put but the Kings Murder and the Proteſtants Maſſacre together, and examine the ſtrange Methods of the Jeſuits for effecting them, and we ſhall plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, that as God hath reſtored His Majeſty by <hi>Miracle,</hi> ſo the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> were reſolved to deſtroy him by <hi>Miracle</hi> too.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe after all, that this Immenſe and Supernatural Courage had not been in them, and that really they knew they had not been able to atchieve all this; why, truly that had been no hindrance to the buſineſs, nor any part of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration; for a Jeſuit in a Plot, when his hand is in, like Sr. <hi>Martin</hi> on the Lute, plays on, and never ſtops at all; and in Seaſon or out of Seaſon troubles not his head. For Example.</p>
            <p>The Jeſuits Fired <hi>London,</hi> with an Intention to Kill the King in the hurry, and Maſſacre the Proteſtants upon't; and yet, ſee the oddneſs of the Deſign,<note place="margin">Nar. par. XXXIV.</note> they laid <hi>London</hi> in Aſhes, and yet were not at all provided to go through with the Work. And why! as the Dr. expreſly tells us, <hi>they were not ſecured of the Duke;</hi> [a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Impediment, when from the beginning of the Plot to the end, they never
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50755:9"/>were, nor hoped to be ſecure of him; the Duke being wholly a ſtranger to their Deſign, and no part of their Truſt, but the whole Family of the Stuarts being poſſitively to be cut off Root and Branch.<note place="margin">Nar. pag 64.</note>]</p>
            <p>And the next Obſtacle to their Deſign was, <hi>the King was induſtrious about the Fire, that they could not find in their hearts to do it,</hi> [a very odd Qualm of pity in a Plotter, and an extraordinary ſtop to a Conſpiracy of almoſt a Hundred Years growth.] - Beſides in this Fire they uſed 700 Fireballs, and thoſe made of <hi>Sheeps Fat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nar. par. XXXIV.</note> no more an Ingredient (to my knowledg) for the Compoſition of a Firebal than for a Sack-poſſet, and might as honorably have been ſworn into one as the other. But the Reader may remember that about the great Fire-time, and ſome Years after, there were a ſort of Thieves had got a trick of Killing Sheep by Night and ſtealing the Fat, as being a more portable, more profitable, and leſs danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Luggage than the Mutton it ſelf, and this Thievery commencing about the Fire of <hi>London,</hi> came pat in the nick for the Fright and Ignorance of the Rabble, to fancy it ſtoln for Fireballs; and the Jeſuits that can improve Fables into Records, found out an Art of putting the Whim into Execution</p>
            <p>Beſides, <hi>in this Fire they pilferd Holland, Cambricks, fine Cloth, ſome conſiderable Quantity of Plate, and a Box of Jewels, in which were One Thouſand Carracts of Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nar. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt up in ſeveral Papers for ſeveral Goldſmiths.</hi> A wondrous ſtock for one Mans keeping, and a vaſt Treaſure, eſpecially of that Lightneſs to be careleſly left behind, to the Rapine of Thieves or Flames. And what's ſtill more remarkable; ſo Infinite was the Wealth of <hi>London,</hi> that amongſt ſo many ſeveral Goldſmiths concerned, not one of them from that day to this, has miſt them or made inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry after them.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The PLOT in <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt here let us take our leave a while of the Rebellions, Aſſaſſinations, Maſſacres, and Fireworks in little old <hi>En land,</hi> and ſee how the Poſture of Affairs ſtands in <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the doing of which we can have no greater Light, than from the Tryal of <hi>Oliver Plunket</hi> late Titular Arch Biſhop of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where indeed we find the whole <hi>Iriſh</hi> Plot ſo to admiration made out, that even Infidelity it ſelf muſt tremble at ſuch undeniable Proofs, and unanſwerable Demonſtrations: and to the Confuſion of <hi>Rome,</hi> all this undoubted Truth delivered by Oracles, ſworn home by no leſs then the very Oaths of Members even of the Popiſh Clergy it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The whole ſumm of which Conſpiracy is as follows,</p>
               <p>Oliver Plunket <hi>was made I rimate of</hi> Ireland, <hi>by the Election of the King of</hi> France, <hi>and upon his Election he made thoſe Conditions with the King of</hi> France,<note place="margin">Tryal p. 84.</note> 
                  <hi>to raiſe Men to joyn with the</hi> French <hi>to deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion, the ſaid</hi> Plunket <hi>having En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to get</hi> Dublin, London-Derry, <hi>and all the Sea Ports into their own hands, to Levy War and Deſtroy the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> (a Vaſt undertaking for a Titular Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to go thorough with) <hi>and that they ſhould have the King of</hi> France <hi>to protect them during Life;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tryal p. 84</note> as <hi>Mac Leigh</hi> ſwears. Upon this Contract we have <hi>Plunket</hi> keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing touch with his promiſe, and undertaking to raiſe 60 or 70000 <hi>Iriſh</hi> to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Joyn with the <hi>French,</hi> as <hi>Duffy</hi> and <hi>Murfey</hi> the two main Witneſſes atteſt, the ſaid <hi>Plunket</hi> having taxed the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Clergy ſeveral Summs of Money, for the carrying on of this War, and maintenance of this vaſt Body of Men, <hi>viz</hi> ſome of <hi>them</hi> 10 <hi>ſome</hi> 20 <hi>nay ſome</hi> 40.<hi>s. p annum,</hi> (a wonderful Summ for ſo Vaſt a Deſign) and himſelf pitch't upon <hi>Carlingford</hi> Haven for the <hi>French's</hi> Landing. This Deſign it ſeems after ſome Years collecting for, and preparation towards it, grew ſo ripe, that as Mr. <hi>O Neale</hi> ſwears, he heard Biſhop <hi>Terril</hi> in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 78. <hi>in the head of</hi> 40 <hi>Horſe alighting at Vicar General</hi> Brady's <hi>Door, give thoſe</hi> 40 <hi>odd Horſemen an Oath which they took willingly from hand to hand, to forward the Plot againſt the Proteſtant R ligion, and to make an end of them all in one hour from End to End of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and ſaid he, I will come within two days with an Order from the Lord</hi> Oliver Plunket, <hi>and you ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d not be afraid, for the Lord</hi> Oliver Plunket <hi>and I, have ſent ſome Gold and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y into</hi> France <hi>to get Men, and bring them from</hi> France <hi>over Sea, and do not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50755:9"/>fear this will go on in one hour through all</hi> Ireland, <hi>from End to End.</hi> (Tho by his good leave I ſhould have much doubted, whether the <hi>French</hi> Men could have kept pace with theſe nimble <hi>Iriſh</hi> Men; for Landing all at <hi>Carlingford</hi> Haven, 'tis much to be feared, they would have made it above Two Hours work, in running through all <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Plot was carried on ſo far, that (as Mr. <hi>Wyer</hi> atteſts) it was to have tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Effect,<note place="margin">Tryal p. 72.</note> and the Invaſion to have been made in 79. a Year after the Diſcovery of the Plot in <hi>England,</hi> he himſelf affirming, <hi>that ſince</hi> Plunket <hi>was taken he ſaw in the time of</hi> Plunkets <hi>Impriſonment his Commands to his under dignitaries, not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of the Moneys, that were aſſeſsed towards the ſupplying the</hi> French <hi>Army, and that there was no better time to bring in the</hi> French, <hi>than when he was in Priſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for ſure Work <hi>Mr. Duffey</hi> atteſts, that this Invaſion was not only to be made by a <hi>French</hi> Army, but by a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army too, that was to land with them.<note place="margin">Tryal p. 77.</note> 
                  <hi>For</hi> Duffey <hi>heard</hi> Plunket <hi>at a Conſult, and giving Special Order for ſome of them to get a Liſt of all the Officers that loſt their Eſtates, and that they ſhould be more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards than they to proceed in that Wicked Deſign, to deſtroy all the Proteſtants together, which was expreſly to be done by an Army, of</hi> Iriſh, Spaniſh, <hi>and</hi> French <hi>together,</hi> Plunket <hi>at the ſame time encouraging every one that could diſpoſe of Money to provide ſome for thoſe Gentlemen, that would ſoon come over into</hi> Ireland, <hi>viz. the</hi> French <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Army together.</hi> Duffy having likewiſe, beſides the ſight of ſeveral Orders for to raiſe Money, ſeen a Letter from <hi>Plunket</hi> when he lay in Jail ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying, <hi>that that was the only time for bringing the matter to an end, and that the</hi> French <hi>and</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Kings ſhould take the Advantage, that now was Offered whilſt he was in Priſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all this <hi>Iriſh</hi> Plot we have a Model of State Affairs extremely different from thoſe in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plot. As firſt for example, we find the <hi>French</hi> King not half ſo Generous in Carrying on the Catholick Cauſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as in <hi>England.</hi> In <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> he was to Lend the Conſpirators an Army <hi>gratis,</hi> and help them to make a Conqueſt for themſelves, whilſt the Vanquiſht Crown and Government was to have been diſpoſed of as <hi>Bellaſis, Petres</hi> and <hi>Arundel,</hi> and the reſt of the Victorious <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Generals thought fit. But in <hi>Ireland</hi> he plainly ſets up for himſelf, and poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and mercinarily ſides with the 60 or 700000 <hi>Iriſh</hi> Champions, to conquer and poſſeſs their Kingdom, nay, he is ſo wretchedly ignoble, that he robs the very Spittle, and ſuffers the poor beggarly Vermin the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Clergy, that were not able altogether to buy Horſe and Arms for 20 Men, not only to be taxt for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their own 70000 <hi>Iriſh,</hi> but likewiſe to ſend over Money and Gold, even to the Mighty King of <hi>France,</hi> towards the bringing his Army over Sea.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we find the <hi>Iriſh</hi> not half ſo valiant, and reſolved in carrying on their Heretick Maſſacre, as the more Heroick <hi>Engliſh</hi> Catholicks in theirs. For the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> (as we have read before) upon the going off of <hi>Pickerings</hi> Gun in <hi>March</hi> 77. were prepared for a Maſſacre, and that too when one Man was to Kill near a brace of Hundreds for his ſhare; But the poor Spirited <hi>Iriſh</hi> in the other Extreme, where the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Party are 50 times more numerous than in <hi>England,</hi> with an Army of no leſs then 70000 Conſpirators all ready for the ſtroke, are cowardly diſtruſting ſo vaſt a Strength, and Calling in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armies to their Aſſiſtance, though to the inevitable Enſlaving themſelves and their Poſterity, to ſo known a Tyrant as the King of <hi>France.</hi> The Foreſight of which Slavery was the reaſon that <hi>Duffy</hi> Diſcovered the Plot, telling us <hi>he had been in</hi> 77. <hi>almoſt a year in</hi> France, <hi>and ſeeing there how the poor People are brought in ſuch Slavery by the</hi> French,<note place="margin">Tryal p. 79.</note> 
                  <hi>he thought of it, and had rather the Devil ſhould reign over them than the</hi> Frenchman.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, we have here the moſt unpolitick, and moſt ſenſleſs conduct in the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> that the Chronicles in all Ages can never parallel: <hi>viz.</hi> We have the King of <hi>Spain</hi> (if there can be ſuch an Animal of a Monarch in Nature) at the very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that he's courting the Alliance of almoſt all Chriſtendom to aſſiſt him againſt the <hi>French,</hi> having loſt ſo great a part of <hi>Flanders</hi> to him, and being ſo much in danger of looſing the reſt of it, is notwithſtanding Lending this very <hi>French</hi> King an Army to help him ſubdue <hi>Ireland,</hi> and inlarge the Conqueſts of his moſt Potent and moſt Formidable Enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50755:10"/>Well: But that Miracles are not ceaſt in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, this would appear moſt Monſtrouſly ſtrange. However for this, and the reſt of the Extravagancies in the Plot, we have all along Subſtantial Oaths, and therefore are bound in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to believe. Tho let me tell you, for a belief in this caſe with his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Majeſties pardon, we muſt lead our Imagination ſo far as to lodge the very Soul of a Changeling in the Breaſt of a King. For a Soul of Gods Common handy Work, could never be ſo void of Common Senſe.</p>
               <p>But, alas! this Blockhead of a <hi>Spaniard (con licenza Signior:</hi> For I vow I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear calling him ſo) is not only Blundering this once, and Committing this one enormous piece of Stupidity: But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plot, and his Affairs there, are of the ſame Leven with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Conſpiracy. For this very King, had not only this Army ready to Land at <hi>Carlingford</hi> Haven, but another of 30000 <hi>Jago</hi> Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims to Land at <hi>Milford</hi> Haven, and 10000 <hi>Flandrians</hi> likewiſe to be Landed at <hi>Bradlington Bay,</hi> and all this at a time when he had ſo many Irons in the Fire, and his hands ſo full to ſecure his own Dominions, and ſo hard a tug at home to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve himſelf; and yet he has no leſs then Three ſpare Armies, of at leaſt half a Hundred Thouſand ſtrong to ſend out abroad. What in the name of Dulneſs ſhould make this Prince court the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Arms to relieve <hi>Mans</hi> for him, when he had no leſs then Three ſuch Powerful Armies, and all lying idle by him, that (one would have thought) might have ſaved him that trouble. Well but that there is a Plot, and has been a Plot. Otherwiſe Mankind had been left in the Dark, and not one quarter of all theſe Apocrypha's had ever been Canonical.</p>
               <p>But as ridiculous as the Plot-craft has hitherto been, we have not only the Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its, and the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> King playing the Fools or Madmen, but even the High and Mighty King of <hi>France,</hi> under the ſame premunire: for Example, was ever a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of his Martial Cunning, ſo Egregiouſly out of his Royal Senſes, and all the Rules of Conduct, as Firſt to Attempt the bringing a Navy into that very Port of all <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo notoriouſly known to Carry ſcarce water enough for a Fiſher-boat, much leſs a Man of War to ride in.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, to conduct his Navy ſo far about, to the very North part of <hi>Ireland,</hi> not only through all the dangerous <hi>Iriſh</hi> Seas; but alſo in the Face of all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ports, and Conſequently through the Mouthes of all the Kings Men of War, that lye in the way, and by ſo long and hazardous a Voyage (eſpecially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Diſcovery of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Plot) to give the Three Kingdoms ſufficient Alarm to prepare for their Oppoſition.</p>
               <p>Beſides all theſe Groſs unpardonable Faults, we have one yet more heinous piece of Lunacy, then Story ever match't. This Fooliſh French King, is at the Charge and Trouble of manning out a Fleet to land an Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> when to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Shame of all ill Memories, both He and all his Stateſmen had quite and clean forgotten they had Landed one there already, for does not the Infallible Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> give us to know, in his Examination before the Parliament, in theſe very words: <hi>That the</hi> French <hi>King had already Landed a great Army in</hi> Ireland, <hi>being thoſe Forces that left</hi> Meſſina, <hi>and it is to make them up</hi> 25000 <hi>which are to Joyn with the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Papiſts, in a ſecond Maſſacre to Fire the City of</hi> Dublin, <hi>and deſtroy the Duke of</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, <hi>and his adherents, and this part of the Conſpiracy was Managed by</hi> Coleman, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
               </p>
               <p>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w what the Devil could make ſo ſubtle a Monarch, ſo ſtrangely Overſeen as. ſo abominably to expoſe a Navy, and a new Army to all the foremention'd ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards, when he had one ſo much better for his turn there already, an Army too of ſo vaſt a Number as 25000, and all Diſciplined Soldiers, being the very For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that left <hi>Meſſina:</hi> nay, and to out-do all yet, an Army even Miraculouſly Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed for the Eruption of a Maſſacre, an Army that had out gone, ev'n <hi>Bays</hi> his Knights-bridge Expedition, having Landed, March'd and Encamped Inviſible being a kind of ſuch <hi>Heterogoneus</hi> Animals, that from that day to this, they had never been Seen, Felt, Heard or Underſtood. But to excuſe the <hi>French</hi> King and the reſt of his Privy-Counſellors, his Armies are ſo numerous, that poſſibly a poor handful of 25000 might not be miſt amongſt them, otherwiſe if he had remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred any thing of theſe 25000 being Landed before, a Force of that Strength, as our <hi>Salamanca</hi> Oracle tells us were to Fire <hi>Dublin,</hi> and Deſtroy the Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50755:10"/>and the Proteſtants his adherents, this laſt Navy and Army, I fancy were to come like <hi>Eſop</hi> in the reer of his Fellow Servan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, to do juſt Nothing, becauſe the former had done all things before. Thus were ſee what humane policies are: <hi>Hamanum eſt errare,</hi> and not only the leſſer Plotters the Jeſuits, but the Imperial Plotters too, even Monarchs themſelves may once in their Lives be overtaken.</p>
               <p>Now 'twill not be amiſs for our Farther Light into this Conſpiracy, to ſearch the Mine from whence the Treaſure comes to defray the charges expended, and to be expended, to ſupport ſo vaſt a Body of <hi>Cut-throats.</hi> And here upon due Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of matter of Fact, for the Carrying on of this fly Plot, we ſhall meet not only great Heads all along, but great Purſes too Employed to Encourage the Laborers and Undertakers in this Sacred Cauſe, inſomuch that wherever the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of St. Ship and Canonizations, and the brighteſt Crowns of Paradice for their Reward, was not of it ſelf alone a ſufficient Spur to their Vigorous Endeavours; when the ſlow Pav of Heaven hereafter was thought a Bribe too little, the Jeſuits never wanted ready Money to make up the Summ. Neither do we ever find them unfurniſht, where or whenever thoſe Golden Tempters were neceſſary. But here as in the reſt of their Affairs we meet with little elſe then the Higheſt Extravagance. For in Diſtribution of their favors to the great Pillars of their Cauſe, we find ſuch Inequality and Partiality throughout, as to their Eternal diſgrace will never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. For Example; what more unconſcionable diſproportion could there be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the 15000. <hi>l.</hi> contracted for, and no leſs then 10000 <hi>l.</hi> bid at firſt word to Sir <hi>George Wak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>man</hi> to povſon the King, and but that inconſiderable trifle of 80 pounds given to the Four <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ruffians, when moſt of them were Gentlemen of as great or greater Quality and Fortune then Sir <hi>George,</hi> and the whole ſumm of 80. <hi>l.</hi> no more than either of them would not have valued ſpending in a Week, nay and when more and above, Sir <hi>George Wakemans</hi> undertaking had not the tenth part of their Dangers attending it, his buſineſs being only the Legerdemain of ſlipping a Pill extraordinary into the Kings Broth or ſo, and Theirs to Aſſaſſinate him in the Face of open Day.</p>
               <p>Or could their be a greater Affront to Perſons of their Quality, to know that honeſt <hi>William, alias John Grove</hi> a poor retainer to the Jeſuits, ſhould have Fifteen Hundred pounds reward for his King Killing Work, and all thoſe Four Gentlemen to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, have but one Twentieth part of the Summ for the ſame Service. This In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity no doubt the Jeſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts were ſenſible of, but poſſibly knowing them to be civil and well bred Gentlemen, they truſted to their Generoſity to forgive it.</p>
               <p>But how cloſe fiſted ſo ever the Jeſuits were in the pitiful Reward of Twenty Pound a Man, to Perſons of their Rank and Character for Killing the King. Yet not long after, their bounteous Liberality was ſomething more open-handed, when they offer'd <hi>William Bedloe, alias, B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dhoe,</hi> originally the Son of a Cobler,<note place="margin">Lords Journ. <hi>Mar.</hi> the 1278</note> and at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a Runner of Errands, no leſs then the ſumm of 4000. <hi>l.</hi> to hire him to Kill Sir <hi>Edmond Bury Godfrey,</hi> and that too, when himſelf was but to be one of the Four or Six that were to do it, witneſs his Oath before the Houſe of Lords. William Bedloe <hi>ſaith on his Oath, that this Examinant being treated with by Mr.</hi> Lephaire, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Walſh <hi>Jeſuits about the beginning of</hi> October <hi>laſt, they offer'd him a Reward of</hi> 4000. <hi>l. if he would be one of the Four or Six that ſhould Kill a Man, that was a great Obſtacle to their Deſigns,</hi> [<hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Edmond-Bury Godfrey,</hi> as it proved afterwards] (a very round ſumm together, if the other Five were to be as well paid) But here the Reader is deſired to take notice, of the moſt matchleſs Example of ſelf Denial in Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> that pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haps they have met with, and the vaſt and wonderful Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſome Mens Conſciences. Thoſe very Gentlemen to whom 500. <hi>l.</hi> was leſs in their Pockets, then five pound in Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi>'s could notwithſtanding bite at 20 <hi>l.</hi> a Man, to Murder no leſs than a King; when on the contrary Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> refuſed 4000. <hi>l.</hi> to Murder but a poor Juſtice of the Peace. For as we have it in his afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Oath before the Houſe of Lords. Thus following, <hi>he this Deponent promis'd</hi> [viz. <hi>to</hi> Lephaire <hi>and</hi> Walſh] <hi>to be one to do it upon their giving him notice; afterwards</hi> viz. (<hi>the</hi> Fryday <hi>before Sir</hi> Edmond Bury <hi>was miſſing</hi>) <hi>Mr.</hi> Lephaire <hi>met him this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent, about Four a Clock in</hi> Grays-Inn-Walks, <hi>and appointed to meet him again the next day, at the ſame place about the ſame Hour to do that Buſineſs: that upon his tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50755:11"/>the Sacrament to do it, he this Deponent ſhould have the Money paid down; but he not liking the Deſign faild of meeting him</hi> &amp;c. Is not this (as I ſaid before) a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful piece of ſelf denial, but as wonderful as 'tis here's the fellow on't to come.</p>
               <p>After Sir <hi>Edmondbury</hi> was murdered, <hi>this Deponent meets</hi> Lephaire <hi>again, and is ſhow'd</hi> Godfreys <hi>dead Body, and upon the ſpot is offer'd half the aforeſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> 4000. <hi>l. to be but only one of the Five or Six,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ibid</hi> Jur. 12 <hi>N</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>that ſhould carry the body to a place where they had Choſe to lay him. To which he ſeemingly agreed, but begging their pardon for half an hour, telling them he'd wait on them again, he went away and came no more; and being charged next day for not coming according to promiſe, Mr.</hi> Bedloe <hi>gave this</hi> Powerful Reaſon for his Abſence: viz. <hi>he was unwilling to come becauſe he knew the Perſon that was Kill'd.</hi> A very cogent Reaſon indeed. But to heighten the Miracle of Mr. <hi>Bedloes</hi> refuſing 4000. <hi>l.</hi> for a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rder; and 2000. <hi>l.</hi> for a Porteridge, the leaſt of them (one would think) a very attractive ſumm; the Reader is to Conſider, that Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> at that very time was none of the ſqueamiſheſt or niceſt conſcienc't Men, being all along not only privy to all the Popiſh Deſigns, the Landing of 20 or 30000 <hi>Jago</hi> Pilgrims at <hi>Milford</hi> Haven, 10000 <hi>Flandrians</hi> at <hi>Hull,</hi> beſides the other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be rais'd in <hi>England,</hi> the Commiſſions given out, and himſelf to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion Officer, and conſequently to be engaged in all the Proteſtant blood-ſhed intended (the Kings only excepted) and that this Man ſhould all of a ſudden ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, at one poor Hereticks diſpatch, tho for 4000. <hi>l.</hi> reward, or if that would not down to refuſe 2000 <hi>l.</hi> and all but for the 6th part of the Luggage of one poor Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, but to <hi>Primroſe-hill,</hi> is not (take it all together) a little ſtupendious.</p>
               <p>But having enter'd into ſo ſad and deplorable a Story, as the Murder of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Gentleman, nothing methinks can ſtrike a greater Impreſſion on all tender Hearts, than the Barbarous Circumſtances and Methods, uſed by his Inhumane But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for his Deſtruction. Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> (for Example) in his former Examination before the Houſe of Lords <hi>Nov.</hi> 12th. has him trappan'd into <hi>Sommerſet-houſe</hi> in this manner. Lephaire, Walſh, <hi>and my Lord</hi> Bellaſis <hi>Gentleman, meeting Sir</hi> Edmond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury <hi>about Five of the Clock by the Kings-head-Inn in the</hi> Strand, <hi>and pretending to bring him to a place near St.</hi> Clements <hi>Church, where they would ſhow him a great Company of the Principal Plotters againſt the King, and Surprize both them and the Principal of their Papers, they walkt on till they came at</hi> Sommerſet-houſe <hi>great Gate, and there made a Halt, deſiring him to walk in, and take a turn or two with two of them, till the Third went and got a Conſtable: here after they had took a turn or two, two more Perſons came out, and ſhoved him into a Room; and when they had him ſecure; They held a Piſtol to his Breaſt, threatning to ſhoot him if he made any noiſe, but if he anſwered their Expectations, they would not hurt him, then asking him to ſend for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminatious, he had taken about thoſe that were Committed, he told them 'twas not in his Power, for he had ſent them to</hi> Whitehall; <hi>upon that, and his refuſing to anſwer other Queſtions they ſeiz'd him, and ſtifled him with a Pillow, and ſo they thought he had been dead, but coming into the Room ſome time after, they found him ſtruggling; and then they ſtrangled him with a long Cravat.</hi> Thus in ample form from the Records of Mr. <hi>Bedloe,</hi> have we the true Hiſtory of this poor Gentlemans untimely Fate.</p>
               <p>But now after this Barbarous manner of Trappanning him, and then Killing him ſtone dead, one would imagine we were come to the laſt Act of the Tragedy. But truly no; there's as bad or worſe behind ſtill, For the kind Mr. <hi>Práce</hi> upon his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovery, has more Bloody Scenes of it to come yet. Upon his Oath before the King and Council, and afterwards confirmed before the Houſe of Lords he ſays, <hi>that</hi> Hill,<note place="margin">Lords Journ. jur. <hi>Dec.</hi> 24 78</note> Green, <hi>and</hi> Gerald, <hi>after a Week or Fortnights dogging Sir</hi> Edmond-bury Godfrey, <hi>they watcht him at laſt paſſing from St.</hi> Clements, <hi>till he came to the</hi> Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate <hi>at</hi> Sommerſet-houſe, <hi>about Nine at Night, where</hi> Hill <hi>making ſome haſt before ſtept within the Wicket, which was open, and turning ſoon again called to Sir</hi> Edmond <hi>as he was paſſing, and ſaid there was two Men quarrelling within, who might ſoon be quieted if once they ſaw him, whereupon he entered through the Wicket, and after him</hi> Green <hi>and</hi> Gerald, <hi>and down all went till they came to a Bench, that is at the bottom of the deep deſcent, and joyning to a rail next to the upper end of the Stables on the right hand, and that upon the ſaid Bench, there was Sitting and Attending their coming the ſaid Examinant</hi> Miles Prance <hi>and</hi> Berry <hi>the Porter of the other Gate, with an</hi> Iriſhman <hi>whoſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50755:11"/>name he knows not, and by that time they were come half way down.</hi> Berry <hi>and</hi> Prance <hi>roſe up from the Bench, and one went up to the Wicket, and the other to the Stone ſteps going up to the great Court, to give notice if any came to diſturb them, and ſo when Sir</hi> Edmond <hi>was got to the Bench,</hi> Green <hi>who followed him whipt about his Neck a large twiſted Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and thereupon they all aſſiſted, and dragged him into a Corner, and twiſted his Neck till they broke it, one of them Thumping him on the Breaſt to make ſure work on't;</hi> and all this without one Syllable of a Piſtol or Pillow, or any Queſtions ask't him, or the leaſt diſpute about ſending for Depoſitions, Papers or any thing like it.</p>
               <p>Here we may obſerve how ſtrangely the Devil helps his Servants: <hi>Hill Green</hi> and <hi>Gerald,</hi> had dogg'd Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey</hi> to the Watergate at <hi>Sommerſet-houſe,</hi> where neither of them ſtirring from him, to give notice of their coming, only <hi>Hill</hi> juſt leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to ſtep into the Watergate, and out again, with the Story of that ſham quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel: yet <hi>Berry Prance</hi> and the <hi>Iriſhman,</hi> are ſitting on the Bench by the Stables, and attending their coming, having the Knowledge no doubt from ſome Infernal Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, not only that <hi>Hill Green</hi> and <hi>Gerald,</hi> were at that time following Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> from St. <hi>Clements,</hi> and that Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> would take the Watergate in his Walk, but alſo that upon the Story of a Quarrel within the Queens Pallace, Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> would Officiouſly thruſt himſelf where he had nothing to do, and all to part a Fray, only with the Face of a Juſtice of Peace, at Nine a Clock in a Winters Night, and that upon that very ſpot of ground within ſight of a Centry, who had Ten times more Authority and Power to do it then he.</p>
               <p>But to proceed with the Villany of theſe Popiſh Aſſaſſinates, that very Night he was convey'd out from <hi>Sommerſet-houſe, Mr.</hi> Lephaire <hi>courts Mr.</hi> Bedloe <hi>with</hi> 2000. <hi>l. to be one with himſelf, Mr.</hi> Walſh <hi>my Lord</hi> Bellaſis <hi>Gentleman and Mr.</hi> Atkins, <hi>Mr.</hi> Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pys <hi>Clerk, to help convey him out,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lords Journ. jurat 12 <hi>N.</hi> 78</note> 
                  <hi>and the next minute Mr.</hi> Bedloe <hi>is ſhowed the Body of Sir</hi> Edmond, <hi>and the aforeſaid Perſons all there, and all ready and agreed to do it, but Mr.</hi> Bedloe <hi>diſliking the Imployment, leaves them by an excuſe, and the next day is chid for not keeping his laſt Nights promiſe of returning and aſſiſting them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> does not finiſh here but finds new matter, and new Nights work ſtill; for he does not only all along leave the Body in the Cuſtody of his own Crew of Murderers <hi>Green, Berry, Hill &amp;c.</hi> but after many a Removal of it upſtairs and down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtairs, from Room to Room, toſt as I may ſay from Pillar to Poſt, the aforeſaid <hi>Green, Berry, Hill,</hi> with <hi>Kelly, Gerald,</hi> himſelf, and one <hi>Iriſhman</hi> more, were the very nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Perſons that carried him to <hi>Primroſe-Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all this admirable Variety mark how pat it falls out: as Sir <hi>Edmond-bury</hi> was found with thoſe <hi>Two fold</hi> marks of Aſſaſſination about him, <hi>viz.</hi> both <hi>Strangled</hi> and <hi>Run Through;</hi> ſo likewiſe 'tis obſervable, that <hi>Two-fold</hi> was the way of Trappanning him, <hi>Two-fold</hi> the Fatal place, and <hi>Two-fold</hi> his Murder (oh how inſatiate is the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Revenge, that <hi>One</hi> Death could not ſuffice) and even to the very laſt, no leſs then a <hi>Double</hi> ſet of Night-walkers are employed, for the Expedition to <hi>Primroſe-Hill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall inſiſt no farther, either upon the Cruelty or Strangeneſs of this Aſſaſſination, and the Appurtenances thereunto belonging, only to reconcile all doubts, that theſe ſeeming Extremes, or what elſe you pleaſe to call them, may not grate the Gentle Reader, let him but inquire farther, and hee'l ſoon learn, that by that time thoſe three Murderers, <hi>Green Berry</hi> and <hi>Hill</hi> were apprehended, and Tryed for the Fact, all Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties were removed; and all Differences adjuſted; whilſt like Eaſt and Weſt as (they ſay) differ but in a point, or like Virtue placed between two Vices, the Golden Mean was at laſt found out, and the aforeſaid three Blood thirſters, received the condign re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of ſo outragious a Crime. And I heartily wiſh, that all the yet undiſcovered Aid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Abettors, or Actors in that Murder had their as juſt, or more juſt Reward.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fiat Lux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to return to our Plot Hiſtory, and the Conduct of thoſe Eternal Blunderers the Jeſuits, one moſt remarkable Obſervation is, that in all thoſe Numerous Letters and Pacquets ſeen and read by Dr. <hi>Oats,</hi> delivered at <hi>Valladolid,</hi> St. <hi>Omers &amp;c.</hi> or elſewhere beyond Sea or received from thence, tho they contain'd no leſs then the whole ſumm of all their Conſults in <hi>England</hi> or elſewhere, and all the ſeveral Propoſals and Methods for Regicides, Maſſacres, Aſſaſſinations, and all the reſt of their Villanies whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; The Jeſuits in all their politicks, were ſuch ſtupid inconſiderate Fools, as to Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50755:12"/>the bringing and carrying of all thoſe dangerous Papers from, and to all parts whatever, with the contents (excepting one or two in Latin or Spaniſh) in plain down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Engliſh</hi> words at length, only now and then intermixing ſuch an inconſiderable Cypher, as 48 for the King, 66 for <hi>London,</hi> or <hi>Barly-broth</hi> for the Parliament: inſomuch that the moſt dangerous Letter Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> ever broke open, without the leaſt trouble of a Key, or the oppoſition of Figures or Characters he read <hi>Ex tempore.</hi> Nay Mr. <hi>Dug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> in the 5 Jeſuits Tryal p. 25, &amp; 26. intercepted no leſs then a 100 Letters, expreſly upon Oath directed to other Men, all containing Treaſon in them for Killing the King, and Introducing of Popery, and all too in plain <hi>Engliſh</hi> without any Cypher at all; and thoſe Letters more and above too ſent by the Common poſt.<note place="margin">Jurat. before the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſe of Lords <hi>De.</hi> 3 78</note> Beſides honeſt <hi>Bedloe</hi>'s the greateſt Plot Meſſenger of them all, ſwears he never carried one Letter or Pacquet, that he did not break open and read.</p>
               <p>And now methinks in ſo ſubtle and hazardous an Enterprize, never were ſuch egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Overſights committed by Men of the Jeſuits Brains, as to venture ſuch notorious Treaſons ſo nakedly dreſt, to all Accidents that might occur; when <hi>Coleman,</hi> who had not one Syllable either of Killing the King, Firing of <hi>London,</hi> Maſſacres in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland; Jago</hi> Pilgrims, <hi>French</hi> Armies; Popiſh <hi>Ruffians,</hi> Black Bills, Piſtols, Ponyards or Poyſons, not only writ but received all his Papers in Cyphers, nay a great many of them too from thoſe very Jeſuits beyond Sea, whoſe hand-writing with a 100 times more dangerous contents in it, <hi>Oats, Bedloe,</hi> and <hi>Dugdale</hi> dayly ſaw and read, without the leaſt veil of Cypher Character or Diſguiſe whatever: when the intercep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of but one of all thoſe innumerable Pacquets, by any Proteſtant hand, had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly deſtroy'd the whole Fabrick of the Plot, and laid both the Papiſts and their Cauſe in unavoidable Ruin. Good Heavens, that a Cabal of ſuch prodigious Undertakers, ſhould moſt of them be Men of ſuch Infinite Learning, and yet to ſo little purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But alas, the Jeſuits were thoſe hardy Deſperado's, that they writ Treaſon, and poſted it about at random, without either Fear or Wit: inſomuch that <hi>Dugdale</hi> after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercepting, and breaking open ſo many of their Plot Letters, ſwears <hi>he kept thoſe he could not handſomely Seal again,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Corkers</hi> Tryal p. 9th.</note> and yet not one Man of the Conſpirators ever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of the Miſcarriage, or made the leaſt Uproar, though for the loſs of Recorded Treaſon in grain. Beſides, as ill luck would have it, Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi> could never find the place where he laid them, nor produce but one of them ſo kept, tho for the ſaving the credit of his Colly Flower'd Face, and preventing his Evidential Carbuncles, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brought in for the ratification of his whole Diſcovery.</p>
               <p>Nay the Jeſuits were that confident pack of Treaſon mongers, that they durſt Preach it even to School-boys; <hi>whilſt they had every day in the Week ſeveral Places, where</hi> Blundel <hi>taught the Youth of</hi> London, <hi>Treaſonable and Mutinous Doctrines againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Perſon of His Sacred Majeſty, and gave certain Summs of Money to their Parents (if poor) to encourage them to ſend their Children to be thus Inſtructed.</hi> And all theſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (it ſeems) ſo grown up as to underſtand Morals as well as Letters,<note place="margin">Nar. par. XIV</note> and yet not one of them from that day to this, ſo unlucky as to tell Tales out of the School.</p>
               <p>I have one piece of Conduct more in theſe Everlaſting Noddies the Jeſuits, and that too likewiſe in the caſe of <hi>Coleman,</hi> which certainly is one of the Idleſt Whims of Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, that ever Stupidity in the Name of Non-ſence could have contriv'd. We find this <hi>Machiavel Coleman,</hi> in the greateſt part of all his Papers correſponding and treating with the Forreign Jeſuits, and all the greateſt Plotters abroad all about Proroguing and Diſſolving of Parliaments, ſometimes puſhing on the project of a Toleration, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwhiles laboring for their Proroguations upon their every leaſt motion in disfavor of the Roman Catholicks. And that this was the Deſign in the very Year 78, we have the Teſtimony of that Gentleman Evidence Mr. <hi>Robert Jenniſon</hi> for it, who in the firſt page of his Narrative ſaith, that about the beginning of the Year 1678. he hath heard Mr. <hi>Ireland</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jenniſon</hi> both Jeſuits, diſcourſe of a Deſign by the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks to obtain a Liberty, or a Toleration for the open Profeſſion of their Religion here in <hi>England.</hi> And the way he then heard them ſpeak of, was by collecting a round ſumm of Money among their party, and by bribing the greateſt part of the then Parliament. Now conſidering at the writing of <hi>Colemans</hi> Letters, and all the time of his Forreign Correſpondency, nay and as long before, as ſince the very Firing of <hi>London,</hi> not only the Sword (as the Plot Diſcoverers tell you) was every day almoſt at the Kings Heart,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50755:12"/>and all the Proteſtants Throats, and <hi>Coleman</hi> himſelf a Perſon ſo deep in the mire, that as the Dr. Swears not only the Firing of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ormonds.</hi> Murder and the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſſacre was managed by him, but himſelf too was the Pay-maſter of the Four <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ruffians, and in fine engaged through the whole Plot. Now conſidering I ſay all this, and that tis plain, what with the Murder of the King, and Maſſacring the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, whether by <hi>French</hi> Armies, Pilgrim Armies or Black Bills, Popery was manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come in by nothing, but open Hoſtility and downright Conqueſt: What the Devil was in the Fools heads of ſo many of the greateſt <hi>Roman</hi> Conſpirators, to be thus ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly day after day at the ridiculous trouble of ſo inconſiderable an Under-Plot, as poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly picqueering at the ſilly Seſſions or motions of a Parliament, when upon murdring the King, and Subjecting the whole Nation by the Sword, not only the Parliament had been Diſſolved, nay and a Members Brains poſſibly as eaſily knockt out as a Plow-job<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; but more than all this, upon the Papal Empires entring by Conqueſt, they might have put an end to the very Conſtitution and Being of Parliaments.</p>
               <p>Why all that Coſt and Labor then, and ſo much waſt Paper in Figures and Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, and ready Money too for Parliament bribing, and all to do juſt <hi>nothing,</hi> if at the ſame moment they had ſo much a vaſter Machine at work to accompliſh even their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Wiſhes without it. Well but as whimſical as all theſe Affairs appear, as I told you all along, the Jeſuits were Infatuated, and through the whole Labyrinth of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, no Man can better ſolve the Phaenomena's he meets, then by ſaying in ſhort they all hang together by Geometry.</p>
               <p>Now after all theſe Fantaſtick, and almoſt incredible Proceedings of the Jeſuits through their whole Plot, ſome People perhaps may object and ſay, that ſuch under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings as <hi>Bedlow, Dugdale, Oats &amp;c.</hi> whoſe chief buſineſs was but running of Errands, and themſelves but a ſort of Goers between to the other greater Plotters, might poſſibly be not fully entruſted with the whole Plot, and therefore by picking up of but ſcraps and hearſays of it, that might probably be the Occaſion of many Stumbles Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Miſtakes in their Diſcovery.</p>
               <p>But to refute that feeble objection, we have the very worſt of them at every turn Hail Fellow at all Conſults with their Lords and Maſters; nay beſides the Letters bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken open by Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> ſcarce one of them all, that ever he carried that was not ſhewed him, <hi>Mr. Dugdal</hi> likewiſe opend all that came down to his Maſters in the Country; and Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> broke open all his. Nay for a farther Confirmation of their great truſt, they had Acceſs to Perſons even of the higheſt Degree. Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> for inſtance, had that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge in the Pallaces of Princes, that he peep't through at leaſt three Key-holes, in as many ſeveral Doors to ſee the Duke at Maſs in a corner of his Cloſet. But little Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> had the greateſt Honor imaginable <hi>viz.</hi> to be by when the Queen was ſnubbed for not conſenting to the Kings Murder. I marry was he, and all this Honor too was done to <hi>Bedloe</hi> a fellow proved at the Five Jeſuits Tryal, <hi>to have been a Priſoner in the Marſhalſea in</hi> May 78. <hi>and ſo poor, as to Live on the Basket;</hi> tho by the bye, the Jeſuits were a little fooliſh here too as well as in the reſt of their Affairs,<note place="margin">p. 76.</note> to let a Perſon ſo long privy to their Deſigns, that Conſequently had their Lives at his Mercy, ly in a Goal, and in ſo much Neceſſity as to be next door to ſtarving; conſidering too they had been ſuch kind Maſters to him, that at <hi>Pickerings</hi> Tryal, <hi>Bedloe</hi>'s Junior ſwears he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived 50 or 3 ſcore pounds a time from them; and not many Months after, he had no leſs than the proffer of 4000 <hi>l.</hi> from them at one clap but for one job of Work: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever (as we have before proved) if no greatneſs of Quality was too high Company for theſe Diſcoverers, and no ſecret concealed from them, there cannot be the leaſt ſhadow for any ſuch objection, and all their reſpective Teſtimony muſt be given in their full and perfect knowledg of the whole Intrigue.</p>
               <p>Nay that was unlikely the Dr. ſhould erre through any of his Affidavits, through that vulgar frailty Forgetfulneſs, we have him a Perſon of that prodigious Memory, that through his whole Examination before Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey</hi> in LXXXI Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs, the whole Subject of above Fifty of 'em is the contents of Pacquets, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Letters too and fro from the Jeſuits from all parts, and almoſt all of them (excepting two or three of them broken open by himſelf) read only in other Mens hands; yet I ſay we have him ſo compleat a Remembrancer, as beſides the wonderful variety contained in them, to give us their expreſs date of the day of the Month, even
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50755:13"/>to the nice diſtinction of <hi>Stylo novo</hi> &amp; <hi>Stylo Vetere:</hi> A taſt of which unexampled Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry I'le inſtance in paragr. LXXII where he ſays as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item this Deponent ſaith, that the Pope hath iſſued out a Bull, a Copy of which Mr.</hi> Blundel <hi>ſhowed this Deponent on the</hi> 30th <hi>of</hi> Auguſt, <hi>in which the Pope was pleas'd to Order and Diſpoſe of the Biſhopricks in</hi> England, <hi>and other Dignities of the ſame as follows</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>CANTERB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cardinal</hi> Howard, <hi>with an Addition of</hi> 40000 <hi>Crowns per annum, for maintaining a Legantine Power and Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>YORK.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perrot, <hi>Superior to the Secular Prieſts, who hath power of probate of Wills Licences for Marriages, and all Epiſcopal Juriſdiction except Ordination and Confirmation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In this manner, the Dr. goes on with Biſhops and Abbots to the number of about 30, without forgetting one ſingle Name or the Latitude of their Juriſdictions; with a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account, by whom the leſſer Dignities of the Church were to be managed &amp;c. And all this <hi>ad unguem</hi> from only the ſight of the Copy of a Bull ſhowed him by <hi>Blundel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But laſtly, to draw towards a Concluſion, for his laſt Entertainment, I ſhall give my Reader the moſt profound piece of the whole Diabolical Plot.</p>
               <p>The Dr. you muſt underſtand, and his Epiſtle to the Reader in his Narrative tells you as much, made the Diſcovery of the Plot to His Majeſty <hi>on the</hi> 13th <hi>of</hi> Auguſt 78. <hi>by the Means and Introduction of that Worthy and Honeſt Gentleman Mr.</hi> Chriſtopher Kirby. And mark ye, after that very 13th. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 24 of his 81 Paragraphs of his Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive are the buſineſs of the Plot, ſtill carrying on to <hi>September</hi> the 7 following, from p. 37 to p. 57. In which laſt part of his Narrative (and all after his Diſcovery to the King) we have the greateſt Tranſactions and Conſults of the whole Conſpiracy. Particularly <hi>that very</hi> 13th <hi>of</hi> Auguſt,<note place="margin">Nar. par. LV. II.</note> 
                  <hi>at</hi> 6 <hi>at Night was the Dr. not deſignedly, but by accident at a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached by</hi> John Keins, <hi>to</hi> 12 <hi>Men poor in habit yet Men of Quality, as the Deponents ſuppoſes, by their white hands, in which Sermon was delivered, that Proteſtants and other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick Princes were</hi> ipſo facto <hi>depoſed, becauſe ſuch, and that it was as Lawful to deſtroy them as an</hi> Oliver Cromwel, <hi>or any other <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper.</hi> Auguſt 18. <hi>the Dr. was at a Conſult, where Mr.</hi> Vincent,<note place="margin">Nar. par. IXI</note> Joſeph David Keymaſh, <hi>Mr.</hi> Dominick, <hi>Mr.</hi> Collins, <hi>Mr.</hi> Fedding, <hi>Mr.</hi> Manſell, <hi>and Mr.</hi> Laumſdale <hi>all Dominicans, met and conſulted with</hi> John Keins, <hi>Father</hi> Hartcourt, <hi>Father</hi> Fenwick, <hi>Father</hi> Wright, <hi>Father</hi> Blundel <hi>Jeſuits, about Killing the King and Carrying on the Deſign; at which Conſult</hi> Oats <hi>was preſent too and fro, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards employed by them to carry the Propoſals of the Conſult to the Carmelites,</hi> viz. <hi>Dr.</hi> Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Mr.</hi> Kimbal <hi>and Mr.</hi> Trevers,<note place="margin">par. LXIII.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> On Wedneſday the 21 of <hi>Auguſt. was another Conſult held by the Jeſuits and Benedictines about the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Affairs, and a</hi> 3d <hi>Conſult at Mrs.</hi> Saunders-houſe, <hi>of which the Dr. had notice before the meeting of it by</hi> John Grove. <hi>Nay the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Ruffians were all Hired and ſent down to</hi> Windſor, <hi>not till after the</hi> 13 <hi>of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,<note place="margin">Par. LXVII.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Dr. by at the telling out and ſending the</hi> 80 <hi>l. after them, expreſly the</hi> 22d <hi>of</hi> Auguſt. <hi>Beſides</hi> Conyers <hi>and</hi> Anderſon <hi>too were not engaged in the Kings Murder till now; for</hi> Conyers <hi>on the very ſame</hi> 22d <hi>of</hi> Auguſt <hi>ſhowed the Dr. his Dagger of a Foot long in the Blade, ſpick and ſpan new bought of the old Cutler in</hi> Ruſſel-ſtreet, <hi>and the ſame</hi> 22d <hi>day does the Dr. meet Mr.</hi> Blundel, <hi>with a Bag of Fire-balls under his arm: and the</hi> 30th <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is ſhowed by the ſaid</hi> Blundel <hi>at</hi> Fenwicks <hi>Chamber (being invited thither to ſee it) a Paper Sign'd by</hi> Whitebread <hi>in the name of the whole Society, containing a Scheme of the manner of Firing of</hi> Weſtminſter, Tooly-ſtreet, <hi>St.</hi> Thomas Apoſtle <hi>and the Kings Ships at</hi> Wapping.</p>
               <p>Beſides we have the Dr. at every turn, at his old ſport of reading of Letters, Packets Memorials <hi>&amp;c.</hi> one time a Catalogue <hi>of the Popes diſpoſal of all the Dignities of the Church ſeen</hi> Auguſt 30.<note place="margin">Par. 72.</note> 
                  <hi>on the 2d of</hi> September <hi>a Pacquet directed to</hi> John Grove <hi>from the Fathers at</hi> Edinburgh <hi>to tell the Fathers here, that they had</hi> 8000 <hi>Catholicks ready to riſe, when the buſineſs grew hot to joyn with the diſaffected Scots.</hi> Theſe Plot Papers cum multis aliis too tedious here to recite did the Dr. peruſe, and went hand in hand ſtill with the reſt of his Brother Plotters.</p>
               <p>In all theſe many Conſults and Matters tranſacted ſince the 13th. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> we find firſt this wonderful ill fortune, that the Jeſuits ſhould meet, conſult, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with as much or more vigor than ever, without the leaſt Breath or hint of a Diſcovery made to His Majeſty from the very 13th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> to the 3d of <hi>September</hi> following.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:50755:13"/>Secondly, we have the Doctor all along as deep in the Plot, and as much truſted by the Jeſuits as ever, and tho he had been with the King to diſcover it, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely Credited by him, endeavored to give him all the ſatisfaction and Confirmation of the Plot, that he could poſſible; yet he neither keeps ſeizes or cauſes to be ſeiz'd, any one of theſe Letters Pacquets Memorials Propoſals or Commiſſions, ſeen or carried too and fro by him; nor ſo much as endeavors to apprehend either the Jeſuits Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans Benedictines &amp;c. at any of their foremention'd Conſults, tho in the height of all their Plotting, with all their treaſonable Schemes, Pacquets, Papers, and Reſolves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them.</p>
               <p>Now ſome unreaſonable diſſatisfyed Critiques, have been apt (God forgive them ſor't) to make this unlucky Dilemma <hi>viz.</hi> that either there were no ſuch Treaſonable Packets, Papers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſeen, read, or carryed by the Dr, nor to be ſeiz'd or produced, nor any ſuch Conſulters to be apprehended; or elſe, that <hi>Titus Oats</hi> inſtead of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Zeal for the King and Proteſtants Preſervation, is the unhappy or rather exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Betrayer of both, whilſt neither the ſafety of his Prince, Country, or Religion could prompt him to make uſe of ſuch favorable and many opportunities, tho for the full Confutation of all Objections whatever, and the Plain and Viſible Detection of the King and Kingdoms Enemies, by ſuch convincing Teſtimonies, as might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronted even Malice, Impudence, nay Hell it ſelf.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, it is to be Suppoſed thàt a Traytor engaged in a Conſpiracy, during the time of his Faith and Truth to that Conſpiracy, might never preſerve any ſuch thing as a Commiſſion, Patent, or any other Treaſonable Paper; and conſequently the Dr. in times paſt, might not take care to furniſh himſelf with any ſuch viſible Proofs againſt them. But from that very day that he repented of his Crimes, abjur'd their Treaſons, and ſided with them only to trepan and betray them, making it his whole buſineſs and ſtudy to furniſh the World with Invincible Proofs of their Villanies, and yet thus egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to let ſlip ſuch numerous Advantages, and dayly offered Manifeſtations of their Rogueries, yes and for this very Diſcoverer to be introduced to the King with no other Credentials about him, than the bare <hi>Tale</hi> of a Plot, and that too in the very height of his giving out dayly Commiſſions for raiſing of Armies <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nay after the Dr. was plainly ſenſible (if he believes as he ſwears) that he had ſeen Pacquets to the Fathers at St. <hi>Omers,</hi> bearing date <hi>January</hi> 1. new Style, <hi>in which the Fathers were aſſured, that His Majeſty of great Brittain was brought to that paſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nar. par. XVIII.</note> 
                  <hi>that if any Malecontent amongſt them ſhould not prove true to their Deſign, His Majeſty would never give ear to their Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation &amp;c.</hi> and yet after ſuch fair Warning, for this very Patriot, that knew he had ſo much Difficulty and Infidelity to cope with, to come thus unprovided, with not one ſcrap or ſcraul out of all thoſe Infinite Manuſcripts and Undeniable Records againſt them, dayly truſted in his hands; for this Plot-ſwearer I ſay, to be thus zealous for the Protection of the King and three Kingdoms, and yet to come ſo empty handed to his Diſcovery, is ſuch a Riddle, Prodigy, or what elſe you pleaſe to ſtyle it, as certainly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had, nor will have the Fellow on't.</p>
               <p>So that through the whole Series of the Plot, we find not only the Motions of the Jeſuits, but likewiſe the very Diſcoverers too, ſo notoriouſly excentrick, that the Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Repreſentation of the Whole, is, If one Pack of <hi>Phaetons</hi> were ſetting the World on Fire, another Pack ſtept out to quench it.</p>
               <p>But that the Jeſuits have ſuch roving Head-pieces, that no Man can fix them to one Point, we might be extremely aſtoniſht, at all the Infinite Diverſities we meet in the Popiſt Plot; and yet as numerous and as Myſterious, as their Methods have been for the Introduction of Popery; <hi>viz.</hi> ſometimes by Maſſacres, another while by <hi>no</hi> Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacres, firſt by Killing <hi>all,</hi> and then by ſaving <hi>half,</hi> one while by <hi>one</hi> Army, and then <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> Army, and afterwards <hi>no Armies &amp;c.</hi> with all the reſt of the forementioned Ya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety: what if at laſt we find out a new Projection for't ſtill, a Projection not ſo much as reſembling any of its Fellows, and poſſibly the very beſt in the whole Bundle. This Projection we find in the 23 paragraph of the Drs. Narrative verbatim as follows.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Fathers of St.</hi> Omers, viz. Richard. Aſhby <hi>Rector, Edward Hall, Edward Nevil, and others of the Engliſh Seminary, did write to</hi> Thomas Whitebread <hi>and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in which was expreſt that it was now apparent, that the Catholick Religion was to be brought in the ſame way, that they had uſed for the Deſtruction of the Father of this King,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50755:14"/>and as that could not be effected till much Blood was ſpilt on both ſides, ſo this muſt be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by Effuſion of Blood,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Here 'twill be worth our while to inquire what that way was, the Roman Catholicks uſed for the Deſtruction of the old King: and for that wee'l go no further than the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Dr. himſelf, in the Epiſtle to his Narrative dedicated to His Majeſty; where after many other Allegations againſt the Popiſh Party, he ſays.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who beſides Theſe were the firſt Authors and Contrivers of the late unnatural War, by their known Diabolical Arts of Inflaming Parties and Paſſions againſt each other, and of your Royal Fathers Sufferings and Barbarous Oſage It was thoſe that brought him to his End, and flouriſh't Swords, and triumphed over his dead Body, whom they durſt not approach when Living,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Aſſertion granted, the Means they uſed for his Deſtruction, and the Effects that follow'd can be no other then theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Papiſts who under the Reign of the old King, by the Indulgence of ſo Merciful a Prince had a private Toleration of their Religion, with a full and perfect Enjoyment of all the Liberties, Priviledges, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities. Peace and I ranquillity, of any of the reſt of His Majeſties Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e notwithſtanding privately enflaming a Crew of Fanatick Traytors to <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> their Prince, deſtroy the Monarchy, and ſet up a Common-wealth to their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable Ruin; and the more artfully to pull down that Ruin, they were moſt of them in actual ſervice for that very Prince they were plotting to deſtroy; thereby not only hazarding their Lives in his cauſe, but likewiſe forfeiting both their Freedoms and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, to the Rapine and Revenge of the Victorious Rebels for their defending him. And all this for the Advancement of Popery; An Odd ſort of Advancement; but let that paſs.</p>
               <p>Now to ſumm up all, if the Fathers at St. <hi>Omers</hi> were unanimouſly agreed, that the apparent means of bringing in their Religion, was the way uſed for the old Kings Deſtruction, and 'tis likewiſe <hi>as apparent</hi> this <hi>only</hi> was the ſaid means; How can we make the Conſpiracy and Byaſs of Affairs in that Age run with this, but by concluding the Papiſts, or their Brethren in Iniquitie for them, are a blowing the old Coal again, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> to raiſe a <hi>falſe Out-cry</hi> againſt Popery and Arbitrary Power, to exaſperate the Kingdom into a Civil War; then mount the Fanatick into the Saddle, and the King to the Block; whiln my old Patrons late Aſſociation was but a Bird of their own hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the ſecond part of the old Covenant to have plaid the old Game over again. And faith, all things conſidered (Papiſts or no Papiſts in the Cabal) this may be the moſt probable of all the Intrigues we have met yet; and how unwilling ſoever ſome People may be to grant this point, if our Dr. ever ſwore truth, the Inference falls ſo pat, and ſeveral late Paſſages look ſo much that way, that 'tis the very Top of all his Diſcovery.</p>
               <p>This unlucky piece of Intelligence ſo <hi>miſ-matcht</hi> to all the reſt of his Evidence, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it got into the crowd, and ſlipt into Print, I know not; but I am certain his good Patrons the Brethren were mightily overſeen at the peruſal of his Papers, in not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating this Luxuriant Branch; and the Dr. Himſelf deſerv'd no leſs then a <hi>True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Pennance for't, and to be turn'd over to Satan to be buffeted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Plot it ſelf is not more Extraordinary, than Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> his good Fortune and Eſcape to prove it; for on the 3d. of <hi>September,</hi> long after his being with the King, he tells us,<note place="margin">Nar. par. 75.</note> 
                  <hi>That he ſaw a Letter from the Provincial, ſpecifying that the Provincial had been Inform'd of ſome Diſcovery made, at which he was ſomewhat ſurpriz'd. Pa.</hi> 76. <hi>the ſame day at Night Mr.</hi> Oats <hi>went to Viſit the Provincial at his Lodging, and was order'd to come again the Morning following. Par.</hi> 77. <hi>the next Morning, being the 4th of</hi> September, <hi>according to the aforeſaid Orders, he went to the Provincial, who upon ſight of him, askt him with what Face he durſt look on him, ſince he had played them ſuch a Treacherous Trick; and ſtruck him</hi> 3 <hi>blows with his ſtick, and a Box on the Ear, and charged him with being with the King and a Miniſter with him, whom he ſuſpected to have Informed the King of theſe things &amp;c. the Provincial having had Intelligence by a Letter from Father</hi> Benningfield, <hi>that had ſuggeſted ſome ſuch thing to him; and therefore judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d it muſt be he that had Diſcovered, and was drawn in by ſome Parſon to the ſame</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But at laſt the Provincial told him, he was willing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to him, if he would diſcover who the Parſon was, and his Name and Place of Abode, to the end he might be ſecured of him, and were reſolved to Kill him: and in the mean time, the Dr. was order'd to go beyond Sea within</hi> 14 <hi>days, as the Provincial ſaid, and that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50755:14"/>might not Cheat them, they were to pay for his Coach-hire, and order'd him entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at</hi> Sittingbourn, <hi>and other places on the Road to</hi> Dover, <hi>and there Mr.</hi> Conyers <hi>at the</hi> Kings head <hi>was to pay for his paſſage to</hi> Callice, <hi>and the Maſter of the Feathers in</hi> Callice <hi>to St.</hi> Omers, <hi>where he was to remain till farther Order from the Provincial.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Aft<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r all this, (Paragr. the 78) on the 6 of <hi>September,</hi> we have the Dr. and <hi>Pick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> conferring Treaſonable Notes together, and the ſame Night we have him coming again to viſit the Provincial.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That about night the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ponent attending the Provincials d or and about to go in, he heard</hi> White <hi>and ſome others whom the Deponent ſuppoſes by their Voices to be Father</hi> Mich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>and one Mr.</hi> Poole <hi>conſulting about the dispoſing of a Perſon he ſuppoſes to be himſelf; their words w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re theſe.</hi> This Man has betrayed us, and therefore we will give a Coachman twenty pound to take him up, and carry him directly to <hi>Rocheſter</hi> to E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quire <hi>Lees</hi> houſe, who lived near the Town, and from thence to <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver</hi> by ſome bye way, becauſe he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted at <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tin bourn</hi> and ſaid, if they could get him on t' other ſide the Water, they would torment him till he had confeſt to them, who it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had been with the King, and Inform'd him of the buſineſs; <hi>When the Deponent heard thoſe Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, he made haſt away and durſt not lye that Night in his own Lodgings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all this is remarkable, that Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> who not many days after durſt not truſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf abroad, without half a ſcore ſtout Beef-eaters, to defend him from Popiſh Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, yet here, after his Diſcovery to the King, and reading a Letter from the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial expreſſing his intimation of the Diſcovery, like a bold Knight-errant ventures him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone at the Provincials own Lodgings <hi>Sept.</hi> 3d, yes, and upon further Orders waits on him again the next day, nay, and what's yet the greateſt piece of <hi>Herculean</hi> Courage, that e're I met with, after not only being tax'd with it, and handſomly cudgelled into The Bargain, but the very Miniſter that drew him in was fairly threatned to be <hi>murder'd;</hi> The undaunted Dr. ventur'd again the 6 day to the Provincials door (tho for n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the World with him) and had went in had not his fortunate over-hearing the Conſult about him, made him troop off in a whole Skin; ſecondly we are to obſerve, that the Provincial that ſuſpected him before, and ſent for him to tax him with it, at the ſame time he had him ſafely <hi>alone</hi> with him, and with no leſs thoughts about him, then Killing the Miniſter that drew him in (which is ſuppoſed was Dr. <hi>Tongue</hi>) to prevent a farther Diſcovery; yet on the otherſide, juſt at the critical minute of unravelling all thoſe Jeſuitiſh Intrigues, that had been an Hundred Years in hatching, fooliſhly even to hazarding their whole Cauſe, lets go the very Man, who had it in his Power to undo them all; a Perſon more dangerous ten times than Dr. <hi>Tonge;</hi> and for his falſehood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the Jeſuits in ſuch a Diſcovery, ten times more deſerving to be ſecured, and to hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his Mouth ſtopt with a Dagger than he; nay what's more lewdly fooliſh than all the reſt, at the very Minute he deſigns to pack him beyond Sea, to prevent farther danger, he gives him 14 days time in Town before he ſets out for Dover. Good Heavens; that the Principal of the Jeſuits in <hi>England,</hi> that one would think ſhould have a little more Wit, one not only ſo highly concerned in the Plot, and ſo induſtrious for the Popes Reſtora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but ſo bloodily principled that <hi>Murders, Regicides</hi> and <hi>Maſſacres</hi> were his dayly Study, ſhould ſo ridiculouſly looſe ſo fair an opportunity of diſpatching, or at leaſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing one poor Renegado, tho for the Preſervation of the Lives and Fortunes of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his whole Party.</p>
               <p>Well! nothing but Folly and Madneſs reigns, and therefore 'twas impoſſible ſuch a Thought ſhould enter into his Head: Beſides as the Drs. Diſcovery, take it altogether, was wholly Miraculous, ſo 'twas ordain'd that Miraculous ſhould be his Preſervation to make it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50755:15"/>
               <head>POST-SCRIPT.</head>
               <p>THis and this only is the Popiſh Plot, as the Diſcoverers give it us, and theſe the particular true Methods taken by the Jeſuits and their Engines, for both the Murder of the King, the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring the Proteſtants, and Subverting the Religion and Government. In this Narrative of the Plot (how light ſoever ſome may interpret the Style I have uſed) I defye the ſevereſt <hi>Plot-hunter,</hi> and the moſt angry Liberty and Property Morger in <hi>England,</hi> to tax me of one falſe Quotation out of the Records of <hi>Titus Dugdale, Bedlows,</hi> or any other of the Diſcoverers. However if my Inferences diſpleaſe them, and any of them have read the Plot with other Opticks then mine: and in fine can kick it into any better ſhape than I have done, I heartily beg he would ſet Pen to Paper, and mend the faults I have made, For I declare I ſhould willingly hear Reaſon, and ſtand Convicted by it.</p>
               <p>But in them an while to return to the Plot. The greateſt part of this Diſcovery is comprized in thoſe fatal Examinations, taken before that unhappy Gentleman Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey.</hi> But ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving named th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fortunate Martyr, I cannot but make one reflexion more on the Jeſuits Infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in that piece of ill timed Cruelty. If I had been one of their Conſult, I ſhould have been ſo far from giving my Vote for his Murder, or one 10th part of 4000. <hi>l.</hi> a piece to his Aſſaſſinates, and all to ſuppreſs the Formidable Drs Depoſitions; that on the contrary, I ſhould have civilly intreated him firſt to have Printed them, <hi>2dly.</hi> have petition'd the 3 Kingdoms, to read them with Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and laſtly have honorably rewarded the kind Dr. for his Diſcovery, with at leaſt a Penſion for his Life. This way I am ſure might have probably ſaved a great deal of Blood-ſhed and more Diſtraction; and I am Confident a Penſion to the Dr. for this ſervice had been better laid out, and better deſerved f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the Popiſh Party, then many a round ſumm expended by them elſewhere for leſs Conſideration.</p>
               <p>This is the Plot, the inſufficient Proſecution of which (as ſome Sham Patriots pleaſe to think, or at leaſt call it) has Exaſperated them into that Gall and Rancor, as has made them brand even the Throne it ſelf, and make the very Government in the Conſpiracy for its own Diſſolution: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Malecontents either cannot or dare not be plain in reciting all the particular Omiſſions and Tranſgreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons committed in that kind, for once I'le do it for them; And ſince the Court and the Court conduct is the great grievance to ſome of His Majeſties true Proteſtant Subjects, I ſhall endeavor to Muſter all the moſt viſible Enormities and neglects, either in the detection of the Plot, or the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion. For Example.</p>
               <p>After no leſs than 30000 <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Pilgrims were juſt in their March towards <hi>England,</hi> were not the King and Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el extremely to blame in ſuch a dangerous Exigence, not to diſpatch Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors to all Forreign Princes, to deny paſſage through their Kingdoms, to ſuch a terrible Legion of Blood-thirſty Vagabonds, and more eſpecially to break Alliance with the <hi>Spaniard</hi> for ſo Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous a Conſpiracy, was it not high time for the ſafety of the Nation to alarum all the Ports of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and draw down the <hi>Militia</hi> that way to keep them out. But this the true Proteſtants know was not done.</p>
               <p>Was it not Likewiſe as great a Neglect in the Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in not Iſſuing out a <hi>Lat tat</hi> or one and Cry, or ſome ſuch thing againſt the 25000 <hi>Meſſina</hi> Soldiers Landed and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd in that Kingdom, and making a ſtrict ſearch for 40000 Black Bills, with a Proclamation likewiſe of ſo much reward to bring in either the Smiths, Ironmongers or Waggoners concerned either in to ging Lodging, or carrying of them.</p>
               <p>Is it not a manifeſt expoſing of his Royal Perſon, to the very great fright of his true Proteſtant Subjects, for the King to venture himſelf to Windſor, or any other of his Country Seats, and Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly but in the head of not above 200 Guards, when no leſs then Four <hi>Iriſh Ruffians</hi> have ſo notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly attempted h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Life there.</p>
               <p>Can there be a more heinous ſcandal to the Government, and the great Men at the helm, after the not only Firing of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Southwark</hi> with 700 Sheeps fat Fire-balls <hi>alias Teuxberry</hi> Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard Balls, but Likewiſe ſuch numerous hands hired and poſted for the Firing of the reſt of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs, firſt not to make a ſtricter inquiſition after theſe Jeſuitical City burners, and <hi>2dly</hi> not to have a ſevere eye upon all Mutton dealers from the Drover to the Butcher, nay from the Cook to the Kitchin ſtuff Maid, to prevent the dangerous uſe of all Sheeps Fat, and that for no leſs then the ſafety of <hi>Englands Metropolis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But above all this; what more unpardonable Fault could His Majeſty commit; or what greater
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:50755:15"/>neglect could he ſhow both of his own, and his Kingdoms ſafety, as not to disband his Guards, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when his <hi>Loyal</hi> Subjects, and the Nations Patriots, for the Protection both of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Faith, and the Faiths Defender, ſo humbly and ſo <hi>Seaſonably</hi> deſired it of him. And what's yet more Capital than all the reſt; neither to reſign his <hi>Militia,</hi> nor take his Forts and Cinque Ports from his Friends, and commit them to their Truſt, whom They his Wiſer Guardians kind Protectorſhips thought fit to chooſe for him. Have not the true Proteſtant Party juſt cauſe (think you) to Exclaim; and in the height of their fervent Zeal for their King and Country, Launch out now and then into a Libel or ſo, upon ſo unconſcionable a Denyal of theſe ſo reaſonable Petitions?</p>
               <p>Nay have not the Brethren a yet more ſevere Complaint againſt His Majeſty, for his Weakneſs of Faith, in not ſufficiently crediting <hi>Dangerfields</hi> receipt of 20 Guinneys from his Royal Highneſs? and that too againſt a Brother, and a Prince, upon the Single Atteſtation of one poor Jail Bird, a Teſtimony not ſufficient to convict a Corn-cutter; nay, and all in down right contradiction of all the other Evidence beſide, who ſtill to the laſt ſwore the Duke both Ignorant and Innocent of the Plot. But alas! what's Innocence in the Face of a Bill of Excluſion; or what ſignity ſuch fooliſh ſcruples as Non-ſence, Improbability, and Contradiction in the Caſe of the Deſcent of Crowns? and why ſhould not that Evidence ſtrike at the Birth-right, nay lives of Princes, and be believed for High-Treaſon at the <hi>C</hi>—<hi>s</hi> Bar, that at a Quarter Seſſions would not have been credited for the Proof of a petty Larceny? Ay, and very good reaſon for it too, for the true Proteſtant Cauſe is a Theme ſo ſublime and ſo Divine, that <hi>ipſo mom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nto</hi> it conſecrates all its Supporters, and puts Oracles even into all Mouths; and the Devil himſelf could ſcarce lye upon that Subject.</p>
               <p>Beſides all Errors at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> have not thoſe unnatural Mothers, the two Proteſtant Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, a juſt Cauſe to bluſh, to ſee themſelves ſo much out done by the more generous Academy at <hi>Salamanca?</hi> Is it not a crying Shame they have not celebrated a Commencement on purpoſe, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Reverend <hi>Dignified Titus</hi> into his Drs. Robes? Nay, are not the whole Body of the Clergy down right Papiſts in their Souls, that they have not with one Heart, and one Voice, made it their humble Petition to His Majeſty, that the ſo well deſerving Pillar of their Religion, may be deſired to lay by his <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Jump, and do them the Honor to Accept of a Biſhoprick.</p>
               <p>Or what more Barbarous Ingratitude could have been ſhewn to the Preſerver of 3 Kingdoms, and the <hi>Atlas</hi> of our Chriſtianity, then that this very Perſon ſhould be ſo heinouſly neglected, that from not being worth 12, <hi>d.</hi> and raiſed afterwards to 12 pounds a Week, he ſhould be 700 worſe for the Diſcovery of the Plot. But alas, that may very well be; for we are all ſenſible he brought over his Diſcovery as <hi>Whittington</hi> did his Cat, with no leſs Expectation then to be made an Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by it; and, as 'tis likewiſe plain, it came upon us very like <hi>Whittingtons</hi> Cat too, no leſs then a Rarity and a perfect Original, being the Firſt and the Laſt either of the Kind or the Price; what greater National piece of Injuſtice can be offered, then that he wants both the Reward and <hi>Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> he deſerves.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, ſome ill natur'd Snarlers are apt to leſſen the Drs Merit, upon ſeveral Lapſes and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes in ſome of his Affidavits; but alas! how inſignificant are thoſe Trifles (like the Spots in the Sun) to the ſhading of his Glory? What if his Infallibility forſwore it ſelf a little at <hi>Drs. Commons;</hi> dares any Man be ſo Impudent as to ſay any thing that he, or any other of the <hi>Narrative</hi> Men ſwore before the <hi>Councel,</hi> or Sir <hi>Edmond-bury Godfrey &amp;c.</hi> how improbable or contradictory ſoever was not Oracle? What if <hi>Elliots Mahumetaniſm</hi> and <hi>Circumciſion</hi> were a little Fabulous, muſt not every tittle therefore of Popery and the Plot-Hiſtory be Sacred Truth? or is it not Down-right turning a Favorer of Popery, and Enemy to the Proteſtant Religion to ſuſpect it otherwiſe? What if he had a little forgot himſelf in his deſcription of <hi>Don John?</hi> and what if before the King and Councel he diſown'd any Perſonal Knowledge of <hi>Coleman;</hi> and yet at his Tryal was intimately ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with him, and the Top Evidence that hang'd him? And what if another time at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, he knew neither Sir <hi>George Wakemans</hi> Perſon nor Hand-writing, or any ill thing by him; and yet at his Tryal poſitively ſwore both his Writing a Treaſonable Letter to <hi>Aſhby,</hi> and the whole Circumſtances of his Undertaking to Poyſon the King for 15000 pounds? Alas; ſhall theſe and Twenty other venial ſlips in the Drs Teſtimony be any blemiſh to the Proweſs and Reputation of ſo Doubty a Diſcoverer?</p>
               <p>Ignorance indeed may prate, and Cynicks may Snarl, and ſeveral of the Drs Oaths, eſpecially that againſt <hi>Elliot</hi> may be the Subject of their Mirth, that do not underſtand it: But alas the world little imagines the depth of that Oath, when that Oath, I aſſure you, is one of the greateſt Atchiev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that ever the Doctor performed for the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Peace, and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For mark ye, the Whigs (ſee what Superſtition can do) were ſo ſtrangely rapt up with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of ſo Divine a Preſerver, and look't upon him as ſo great a Guardian Angel to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Cauſe, that they Styled him no leſs then the <hi>Savior of the Nation,</hi> a Title ſo arrogant as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50755:16"/>out did the greateſt <hi>Roman</hi> Canonizing; till the Careful Dr. troubled at their miſtaken Adorations, to reſtore them to their right Proteſtant ſenſes again, and prevent this more then <hi>Popiſh</hi> piece of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry,</hi> very generouſly reſign'd his borrowed Divinity, and kindly <hi>forſwore</hi> himſelf, only to ſhow he was but Humane Fleſh and Blood. Yes kindly indeed; and may the World acknowledge it: And ſo may the Eyes of the Nation be opened by it, till for the future Men ſhall <hi>weigh</hi> before they <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive,</hi> and <hi>think</hi> as well as <hi>hear.</hi> Till neither Figments nor Phantoms, Incoherencies nor Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be impoſed upon them for Goſpel; nor the Artifice of falſe Alarms, and falſe Fears fright them into a true Diſobedience. So may our Jealouſies dayly leſſen till our Concord increaſes, and the Beſt of Kings be univerſally Loved and Obey'd by the Beſt of Subjects.</p>
               <p>Why, alas! ſhould the Apprehenſion of Imaginary Dangers put us into real Diſtractions; how much is it below the very Courage of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Man, to fancy the Papiſts able to cut our Throats? for my Part I am ſo far from granting the Suppoſition of a Maſſacre, to be made by the <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> hands in <hi>England</hi> (I mean of late Years,) that I defy the Eloquence of Angels, to convince any rational Man of the Poſſibility of any thing like it. And truly amongſt all the falſe Doctrines of the Plot, tho I have been as bold a Pamphleteer as moſt Men, and poſſibly could have rigg'd out a feeble Argument, in as gay Trappings as my Fellow ſcriblers; yet I vow I had never Rhetorick enough, or indeed had never ſo much Impudence, amongſt all the Gorgons through both my Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, as to defend that Bug-bear, call'd a <hi>Maſſacre.</hi> And I am certain if Popery had no other Door for it's Entrance, the Jeſuits might e'en as well have contriv'd to have brought it in by a <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, and perhaps the better way of the two. Inſomuch that I have read that Fate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing Line under <hi>Sir Edmond bury Godfreys</hi> Picture</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Had He not Dyed, We had not Liv'd.</hi> Without up lifted hands for our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. For truly, I was ſo little of the Authors Faith that writ it, that I fancy if that poor Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman had eſcaped that Execrable Murder, both he, and many a ſcore of Thouſands of his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Country-men, had been in a fair way of living, till the Papiſts Hearts aked, and of ſeing 7 and 7 merry <hi>Chriſtmas</hi>'s after it.</p>
               <p>But one thing I have obſerved. Of all the Liberty and Property Men, and the reſt of the great Patriots for the Proteſtant Cauſe, that have hung the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Swords but in a Thread over our Heads, and ſo often alarm'd us with Maſſacres, in all this long Licence of the Preſs, and the Loads of Pamphlets written on that Theme, through all their Pains-taking to convince the World our Throats were <hi>all</hi> to have been cut by the Papiſts, there's not one of them has told us <hi>How</hi> and <hi>which Way.</hi> And truly there's good reaſon for it: That part of our Danger is ſo extraordinary Gigantick, that as not being <hi>in rerum Naturâ</hi> tis only to be <hi>Suppoſed;</hi> and the Papiſts in that Deſign were much in the Caſe of that Philoſopher, that briskly vapored</p>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>Give me but place on which my Feet may Stand,</l>
                  <l>From their fixt Baſe I'le throw both Sea and Land.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And no doubt he would have kept his Word; only the Miſery on't was, The Philoſophers <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> was never found out, and ſo the Feat was never performed.</p>
               <p>But now Suppoſe we laid the Maſſacre aſleep a while, and let the <hi>Jago</hi> Pilgrims take a turn home again; and what if for once we ventured to call in all the Doctors Commiſſions, and disbanded the innumerable Thouſands and ſo forth; and then, (inſtead of the Charge and Trouble of <hi>Pickering, Grove, Conyers,</hi> the four <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ruffians, and the reſt of the Bilboe Sparks, and all thoſe more dangerous barefac't Aſſaſſinates) take the moſt Probable way of advancing the Catholick Cauſe: for Example, Let us Suppoſe the Jeſuits had kept only Sr. <hi>George Wakeman</hi> in pay, and by his dexterity of hand had Slyly taken of the King, unſuſpected by the World, and mounted a Popiſh Succeſſor more Calmly into the Throne, without the open Murder of the King, to Set the whole Kingdom in a Flame, and poſſibly raiſe that unquenchable Fury againſt the whole Popiſh Party, that might not have Stop't till it had acted a ſecond part in <hi>England</hi> of <hi>Cromwels</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Imagine, I ſay, that the Jeſuits had taken this Courſe, and gotten the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of a Popiſh Sovereign in Quiet Poſſeſſion of the Imperial Crown; nay &amp; a Prince too moulded to their own hearts Liking, and would make their Moſt of him; what wonderful Exploits could He and they together atchieve for the Subverſion of the Government, and Eſtabliſhing the Popiſh Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, 'tis an Eaſy thing to muſter up all the Cruelties of Queen Mary's Reign, and All the Breach of her Oaths to her Proteſtant Subjects; and from that threadbare Theme cramp out Matter enough to patch up a Scarecrow to fright the Ignorant Rabble both out of their Wits, and their Allegiance for fear of Popery; tho God knows with no more Reſemblance between the preſent
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50755:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>State of <hi>England,</hi> and that in Queen <hi>Maryes</hi> Days, then between <hi>Bedlows</hi> and <hi>Prances</hi> way of Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering Sir <hi>Edmond,</hi> or the two moſt Oppoſite Things in Nature. Alas! ſhe lived in an Age when the Majority of her Parliament were Papiſts, &amp; the very Reſtoration of the <hi>Pope</hi> came in by <hi>Law;</hi> and when her Smithfield Bonfires blazed ſhe had a <hi>Decretum eſt Lege</hi> for <hi>Hereticis Comburendis,</hi> and waved her Bloody Enſigns under the Standard of an Act of Paliament: but had her Fire and Faggot Statute been as down the Wind, and as little in force as now, I queſtion if ſhe, and all her bloody Councellors, her <hi>Bonner, Gardiner,</hi> and the reſt of them, durſt have Ventured to Set their Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field a Smoaking, unleſs they had a mind to have had her Pallace have Smoaked after it. Neither do we ever read, in all her Popiſh Bigottry, that ſhe and her Zealous <hi>Philip</hi> with all their Spaniſh and Engliſh Power together, and in all their kindneſs for <hi>Rome,</hi> durſt venture ſo much as to reſtore the <hi>Pope</hi> but his Abby Lands again, or ſet up any thing, that but lookt like Arbitrary Government. And why, if we had a Popiſh Succeſſor in our Age, he ſhould dare do ten times more then She, and yet without the 20th part of her Power to effect it, I profeſs I am to learn. 'Tis true the Popiſh Character gives you a great many dreadful Features of that devouring Monſter Popery, and as I remember, it goes ſo far as to bring a Popiſh Succeſſor to a downright <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> at laſt, with his <hi>fiery furnaces no leſs then</hi> 7 <hi>times hotter then Ordinary;</hi> but there as ill Luck would have it, it breakes off abruptly, and never gives the Reader Account, <hi>how</hi> and <hi>where</hi> a Popiſh Succeſſor ſhall find thoſe hardy <hi>Brittains,</hi> that like <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Captains will burn themſelves to throw Us into fire; and without that Latter part the Story's imperfect. For the Introduction of Arbitrary Power, Popery, and Smithfield Piles in this Age, is an Attempt will be ſo <hi>hot</hi> in the Fingers, that it will ne'er be handled without Mortal Danger to the Undertakers. When the <hi>Phaeton</hi> Spirit ſets a driv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Phaetons</hi> Fate muſt follow; and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch that takes that way of ſteering would quickly to his own ſad Coſt find himſelf a King not of Men but of Devils. For if the Shadow and Chimera of Arbitrary Power, and Popery, can raiſe ſo troubleſom a Ferment in the Stiffneckt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England,</hi> the Subſtance of it will do worſe: and <hi>Rome</hi> that now has been Ages a falling (let the Jeſuites flatter themſelves, as they pleaſe, or the Dr. for them) will never be rebuilt in a Trice.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe a Popiſh Succeſſor either could, or would be the very greateſt Monſter that Dreams or Fears would paint him, yet The very Inſpired <hi>Oedipus</hi> of the whole Whiggiſh Party, the Dr. him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has over and again cleared his Royal Highneſs from the Poſſibility of being that Creature. For in his Nar. par. XXIV. after the receipt of a Letter from the Dnos of St. <hi>Omers, which gave the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Fathers Inſtructions to feel how the Duke ſtood affected to their deſign a foot, we have no leſs then</hi> Thomas Whitebread, John Keins, Bazil Longworrh, Richard Petres, John Fenwick, <hi>Father</hi> Ire land, <hi>Father</hi> Harcourt, <hi>Father</hi> Blondel, <hi>Father</hi> Matthew Wright, <hi>Father</hi> Jenniſon, <hi>and Father</hi> Simmons <hi>all Subſcribing this anſwer:</hi> Viz <hi>that tho they had found the Duke a good Catholick, yet he had a Tender Affection for the King, and would ſcarcely be ingaged in that concern: and if they ſhould intimate their Deſign or Purpoſe to him, they might not only be fruſtrated of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, but alſo might looſe his Favor,</hi> Nay we have the Duke ſo far from being thought a Prop of their Cauſe, that his Life is ſeveral times in the Plot, no leſs threatned than his Brothers, <hi>Whitebread</hi> tells <hi>Aſhby</hi> at St. <hi>Omers June</hi> 10th. 78, <hi>that if the Duke ſhould ſet his Face in the leaſt meaſure to follow his Brothers Foot-ſteps, his paſsport was made to lay him aſleep too.</hi> Nar. par. XXIX. and in par. LX. wee have <hi>Keinsv</hi> telling <hi>Oats that the Duke was not the Strength of their Truſt, for if</hi> James <hi>did not comply with them, he muſt go to pot too.</hi> Nay we have the Dr. before the Houſe of Lords, (Octob. 30.78.) upon his being informed that <hi>Coleman</hi> had highly Impeached the Duke of <hi>York</hi> by Letters; comeing voluntarily to clear his Royal Highneſs, and giving ſix ſeveral Reaſons to prove he thought the Duke was wholly Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. The Firſt of theſe Reaſons was, that the Plotters had got a trick to counterfeit his and her Royal Highneſſes Hand and Seal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now if the Doctors Teſtimony be their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Confirmation for all the Villany of the whole Popiſh Plot, why not likewiſe of the Dukes Innocence and Ignorance of it; and if ſo, why ſhall that Prince of Morals ſo oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to the Jeſuites deſigns, that his very knowledge of them had by their own confeſſion been enough to have ruin'd both their Plot and them: A Prince though by their own Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo good a Catholick, yet in his Nature ſo averſe to any Irregular Act, though for the crowning even that great Work that <hi>Rome</hi> and all her Engines had been labouring to perfect ever ſince Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days; how is it likely, I ſay, that a Prince thus Principled ſhould upon Mounting the Throne, turn a <hi>Domitian, Caligula, Nero,</hi> and what not, and be all thoſe Devils, that either the Fright of Fools, or the Malice of Knaves has repreſented him.</p>
               <p>But that neither Prejudice nor Ignorance ſhould fly in my Face, and think this Treatiſe deſigned for the ſtifling of Truth, and leſſening the Popiſh Guilt, I will give them yet a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confeſſion of my Faith. I believe that ſuch a half-witted Zealot, or ſo over-believing a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50755:17"/>Wreteh as <hi>Pickering</hi> might have that confidence in the Popes Key, that for the Aſſurance of Paradice, and 30000. Maſſes he might be hired to Piſtol the King. And yet I declare, I neither think <hi>Pickering</hi> the beſt Gunner for that adventure, nor that his <hi>Pericranium</hi> was able to throw the Murder of the King upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> as <hi>Dugdale</hi> has it: Nor that Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> in <hi>January</hi> 77. read a Letter at St. <hi>Omers</hi> containing a matter of Fact not committed till the <hi>March</hi> following: I cannot believe neither that Mr. <hi>Elliot</hi> was Circumciſed, or had Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his Patron, and that the Doctor in <hi>Foro Conſcientiae</hi> was not as much perjur'd at Doctors <hi>Commons,</hi> as he he could have been at the <hi>Old Bayly.</hi> And though I moſt heartily abhor the <hi>Iriſh</hi> and <hi>Pariſian</hi> Maſſacres, and the Helliſh <hi>Gun-Powder-Plot,</hi> or any other of the Popiſh Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies whatever; yet I declare if any Man ſhould ſwear that <hi>Guido Faux,</hi> or Father <hi>Garnet</hi> had had an Inviſible Army of 25000. Soldiers landed at <hi>Barn-Elms,</hi> and a <hi>French</hi> Navy Riding in <hi>Chelſey-Reach:</hi> I vow from the bottom of my Soul, I ſhould not believe him. And I am ſo far from thinking that any reaſonable Creature ought to pin his Faith only upon Oaths for his Credentials, or that all Accuſations muſt be true, becauſe they are alledged againſt Rogues and Villains, that on the contrary I'le lay little <hi>Tuus</hi> a Wager, that tis poſſible to draw up a Narrative (if he'll be but ſo kind to ſwear to it) againſt a <hi>Judas,</hi> nay the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf, that ſhall not have one ſyllable of Truth in it. Alas! tis my opinion, the greateſt Monſters of Men may be belyed, and he is equally guilty of Perjury that ſwears falfly againſt a <hi>Barrabas</hi> as againſt a <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now ever ſince the firſt Diſcovery of all theſe Helliſh Conſpiracies, and all the hideous and bloody Matters in Agitation by the Papiſts, one thing is ſtrangely Remarkable, none are ſo vehement againſt Popery and Plots, and ſo loud againſt Arbitrary Government as the Diſſenters. In my Opinion the Epiſcopal Party were no doubt in as great danger from the Papiſts as the Non-conſormiſts. Their principles are as oppoſite to the Romaniſts, and I am ſure their Preachers, as Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln, Pierce, Stilling fleet, Tillotſon,</hi> &amp;c. have done the Popiſh Religion more miſchief than a thouſand <hi>Baxters</hi> or <hi>Owens;</hi> for which they and their Diſciples ought in all Reaſon to expect as fatal, and as univerſal a ſtroke from the Popiſh Swords as the Diſſenters; and yet methinks there muſt be ſomething more than ordinary in the Wind, that the Diſſenters of all the Nation, are the greateſt and almoſt only Dreaders of that unexpreſſible Inundation of Popery that was juſt pouring down upon us, with all thoſe Torrents of Treaſons, Fires, Maſſacres, and Rebellions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo extraordinary apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of it, till they make each Part and Tittle ſworn on that Theme ſo abſolute an Article of their Creed, that their Faith is ſtronger than an Eſtriges ſtomach, and can digeſt even In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtence, Romance, and Contradiction. Nay they'll puſh it farther ſtill, and arraign even Majeſty it ſelf, and with all the moſt virulent Exclamations, make the Prorogations and Diſſolutions of Parliaments a palpable encouragement of the Conſpiracy, whilſt the reſtleſs Malice of the Jeſuits is (they'll tell you) at this very day as active, and the Plot no doubt as vigorouſly carrying on as ever.</p>
               <p>Now whether all theſe terrible Apprehenſions againſt Popery be unfeigned, and from the bottom of their Hearts is the thing to be Examined: for Experiment of which, ſince no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Power can faddom Thoughts, we can have no plainer Proofs or Signs of their Faith then by their Works; an Inſtance of which I ſhall give you in ſome few Particulars.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> Swears, that <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Southwark</hi> were Fired by the Papiſts, Nar. par. XXXIV. and <hi>Irelands</hi> Tryal p. 32. and Nar. par. 71. he gives us a full Relation how himſelf, and the Lord knows who beſides, were hired to Fire the reſt of the Suburbs in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 78, and that his words are no common Authority, there's ſcarce a Diſſenter amongſt them that will not confidently averr to this very day, that he believes the Fire at the <hi>Temple,</hi> and <hi>Wapping,</hi> and indeed every conſiderable Fire of late Years has been done by the Treachery of the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, I would gladly know how many Rich Presbyterians ſince the Plot, in whatever part of <hi>London</hi> diſperſt, have ſold their Eſtates in Houſes to the unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tories, or refuſed to lay out their Money for a Common Market price, even in thoſe very Eſtates, that are every day incident to ſo much Ruin, and continually expoſed to the Malice of ſuch fatal and reſtleſs Enemies. Nay what is yet more ſtrange, ſince the late En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance Office has been up, how comes it about in a City, that has above 10000 Houſes in the Diſſenters poſſeſſion, there is not yet 3000 Houſes enſured of all Parties; conſidering too that but the laying out of one five Shillings <hi>per annum,</hi> ſecures no leſs then a 100 pounds. Lord that the Brethren ſhould have ſuch Expanſive Faith in Fires and Sheeps Fat Fireballs, and ſee ſuch frequent and terrible Examples of them; yet ſhould nevertheleſs be ſo ſtrangely negligent, in ſo critical a Juncture, as not to expend ſo little a Trifle tho for ſo important and ſo vaſt a Security. Beſides if Popery were ſo near upon us, and the <hi>Pope</hi> had ſo many
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:50755:17"/>hands at Work, and all reſolved to make Reprizals of his loſt Ground in <hi>England,</hi> I wonder how it comes about, that the price of <hi>Abbey</hi> Lands is fallen no lower.</p>
               <p>In another parr of the Doctors Narrative, we have no leſs then 20000 <hi>Fighting Papiſts in or about</hi> London <hi>all ready to riſe in</hi> 24 <hi>hours. (par. IX,)</hi> and thoſe 20000 like <hi>Falſtaffs</hi> Blades in Buck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on run up afterwards by <hi>William Bedlows</hi> to 40000 (Lords Journal 12 <hi>Nov.</hi> 78) and all to cut the Proteſtants Throats. And if the Plot be ſtill carrying on, no doubt they are ſtill in the ſame readineſs to do the former Execution, and if ſo, I deſire to know how many of the Diſſenting Brethren throughout <hi>London,</hi> in this Plotting Seaſon barricado their Doors with one Bolt, Chain or Bar Extraordinary when they go to Bed, to keep their Throats the better from being cut before Morning. Beſides notwithſtanding all their Outcries againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and the pretended Court Encouragement for the Blood-thirſty Papiſts to proceed with their Inſurrections Armies Maſſacres, and all the reſt of their Roman Thunder-bolts, I would willingly ſee a Liſt of all thoſe rich Diſſenters that have ſold their Patrimonies at home to remove to <hi>Carolina, Penſylvania New-England,</hi> or any other Forreign Sanctuary to eſcape the <hi>Popiſh Blood hounds,</hi> tho for the Preſervation of both the Eſtates and Lives of themſelves and their Families. 'Tis true the Suppreſſion of their Conventicles has done much that way, and ſent ſeveral of them outwards bound. But if the 25th of Tory <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had been repealed, or but the Kings Indulgence continued, tho the 40000 Black Bills had run up to Seed, and increaſed to Ten-fold the number; tho the <hi>Jago</hi> Pilgrims, <hi>Meſſina</hi> Soldiers, and the reſt of the Papiſts Militant had been improved into half a Million; and the Plot it ſelf made ten times a greater <hi>Garagantua</hi> than tis, I had defied them all from frighting one of them hence. Now certainly if the Diſſenters believed as they ſay, and that all thoſe daily imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from Popiſh Swords, and ſo univerſal a Deſtruction ſtill threatning us were a true Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of their Belief, 'tis to be admired we find ſo few or none of their Actions to demonſtrate their Fear's in Earneſt. Their Fears in earneſt? no, the wiſer Heads amonſt them know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things, and Fears, Plots, and Jealouſies their old State Tools, are uſed always as Boys do Vizors, to fright every body, but themſelves that wear them.</p>
               <p>And what is and ever has been for theſe 40 Years laſt paſt, the Confuſion and Ruin of three Kingdoms, but ſetting up of Shadows and <hi>Chimera</hi>'s like ſo many <hi>Ignes fatui</hi> to miſlead deluded Ignorance into Diſtraction and Rebellion, whilſt the great Knaves traile the Carrion, and the little Fools hunt after it.</p>
               <p>For let the Whiggs take it as they pleaſe, they cannot be divided but into two Claſſes. They amongſt them that are ſo ſhallow as to believe a hotch potch of Incongruity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction for Truth are Fools; and the greater and Wiſer Men amongſt them that I am ſure have better Intell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cts, and yet notwithſtanding by all the Arts, and Study endeavor to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that upon weaker underſtandings, what they do not believe themſelves, are Villains; and whilſt they make it their buſineſs to uphold Lies and Shams, are ſo far from what they pretend themſelves Patriots, that they are nothing but Incendiaries, whilſt the National Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is but the pretence and their own Revenge or ſiniſter Intereſts the great end they drive at.</p>
               <p>The effects of which all good Subjects ought to their utmoſt endeavours and capacities to prevent, and the whole buſineſs of this Treatiſe is for no other deſign, that Noiſe and Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence may uſurp no more, but Sence and Reaſon ever reign in Peace, till the great Diſturber of the World, Falſe Fear, be baniſh't from our Borders, and Unanimity and Obedience ever Flouriſh amongſt us in <hi>Secular Seculorum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now to take my leave of all Republick Projects and ſtate Cheats; and alſo to find a Compariſon black enough for the late Damnable Plot, I cannot liken its Appearing in the world better than to ſome deform'd Hagg, with Paint Patches and Perfumes coming into a Maſque; what with the help of good Trappings, good Fucus, good Plaiſtering and other Embelliſhments, at firſt ſight by Candle-Light ſhe appears pritty enough, till having danced too long to a <hi>Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> Jigg, at laſt her Paint begins to melt, and the poor Thing is forced to withdraw; where after laying by her falſe Curls, her falſe Teeth, and her Glaſs Eye, Monſter and Deformity e'en goes to Bed, and is juſt now falling aſleep.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
